<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Adam unvailed, and seen with open face or, Israel's right way from Egypt to Canaan, lately discovered. Wherein his estate is laid down, opened and compared with ours, under severall dispensations; in opposition to what ever hath been formerly declared by most men: in which many excellent truths appear, to the great comfort and consolation of all those that are made capable of it. By William Rabisha.</title>
            <author>Rabisha, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1376_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209250</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868136</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868136</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91675)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 180:E1376[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Adam unvailed, and seen with open face or, Israel's right way from Egypt to Canaan, lately discovered. Wherein his estate is laid down, opened and compared with ours, under severall dispensations; in opposition to what ever hath been formerly declared by most men: in which many excellent truths appear, to the great comfort and consolation of all those that are made capable of it. By William Rabisha.</title>
                  <author>Rabisha, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the black spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Adam unvayled.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fall of man --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ADAM UNVAILED, AND Seen with open Face: OR, Iſrael's <hi>right way from</hi> Egypt <hi>to</hi> CANAAN, Lately Diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Wherein his eſtate is laid down, opened and compared with ours, under ſeverall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, In oppoſition to what ever hath been formerly declared by moſt men: In which many excellent Truths appeat, to the great comfort and conſolation of all thoſe that are made capable of it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Rabiſha.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 15. 46, 47.</bibl> Howbeit, that was not firſt which is ſpirituall, but that which was carnall.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 51. 29.</bibl> In thoſe dayes they ſhall ſay no more, the Fathers have eaten ſowr grapes, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>London, Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black ſpread-Eagle at the weſt end of Pauls, 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169878:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169878:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Fountain that is made bitter, cannot ſend out ſweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant waters: nor a building that is ſet upon a ſandy Foundation cannot ſtand; but either the waters will annoy thoſe that drink thereof; or the building will fall on thoſe that dwell therein.</p>
            <p>Therefore I have conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the firſt principles of
<pb facs="tcp:169878:3"/>
Chriſtian Religion, on which almoſt all the other Principles have ſome dependance; namly, <hi>Adams</hi> eſtate in Innocency; and alſo his eſtate after his Fall. And upon ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I have found, that the Star called worm wood, hath had ſome influence upon this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and hath made it bitter, as it hath alſo other rivers and fountaines of waters, which are the pure Doctrines of Chriſt, ſo that as many as have drank of that imbitter'd waters, are rather poyſoned then any ways by it refreſhed: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this River or Fountain, or principle of <hi>Adams</hi> eſtate in innocency, being corrupted
<pb facs="tcp:169878:3"/>
and made bitter, on which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the principles neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be beleeved have ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance; therefore this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple being corruped and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened it will neceſſarily follow that the other principles have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their dependance on this, wil alſo be corrupted and made dark by this; and ſo there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a cleer underſtanding of any truth, this firſt principle being not truly underſtood; therefore ſince God hath given me ſome light in this thing, I have been exceedingly preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in my ſpirit to make known what God hath made known unto me, to the end that you may be made one with it as I
<pb facs="tcp:169878:4"/>
am, and ſee your ſelves and your fall, and not anothers fall; and ſo by your fall you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtand <hi>Adams</hi> fall, for none can underſtand a thing until he be apprehenſively made one with the thing to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; for what is the reaſon of all the confuſion in the world, but one ſeeing with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans eyes, handling with another mans hands, hearing with anothers eares, and taſting with anothers palate, they being not made apprehenſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of the things they hold? Therefore Reader I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you not to ſee with the eyes of others, but with your own; beleeve not this old prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,
<pb facs="tcp:169878:4"/>
becauſe the multitude and almoſt all Chriſtians hold it to be a truth; for truth is not commonly found with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; witneſs <hi>Noah,</hi> who was oppoſed of all men but of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven perſons; and alſo <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> who oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Preiſts of the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and <hi>Daniel</hi> and the three Children, with all the people of God both before and after, being few always in number have ever been in oppoſition to to the whole world; as alſo of late times <hi>Luther</hi> withſtood the Preiſts and Monkes of all Nations with the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and all oppoſers thereof, who moſt excellenly did purge the worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood
<pb facs="tcp:169878:5"/>
out of ſome of thoſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Fountains of waters as were poyſoned by that ſtarre which burned like a torch: Therefore becauſe the whole world hath been befooled in all ages, and alſo the wiſe of the world is threatned to be fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for God hath ſaid that he will deſtroy the wiſdom of the wiſe, and bring to naught the underſtanding of the prudent, and uſe the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and the baſe things of the world to confound the mighty, and the things that are not to bring to naught the things that are. Reject not ſuch fooliſh, ſuch weak, ſuch baſe, ſuch things
<pb facs="tcp:169878:5"/>
that are not, leſt in rejecting ſuch, thou reject the meanes which God hath always decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Councel by and ever wil; truſt not any, try all things, hold faſt that which thou art made one in, without learning from another man as a <hi>Parret,</hi> and earneſtly deſire the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Gods Spirit, and the Lord give thee underſtanding to Judge of the things that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the fellowſhip of the Spirit, and Miniſter of God according to the diſpenſation of grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto him. WILLIAM RABISHA.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:169878:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169878:6"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe common oppinion touching <hi>Adams</hi> Eſtate laiddown. p. 1.</item>
               <item>Adam was made carnall without holineſs and righteouſneſſe. ibid.</item>
               <item>Adam loſt nothing by his eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit but gained by vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. p. 2.</item>
               <item>1. Proved from the name of the trees, what the two trees in Paradiſe are ibid</item>
               <item>2. Proved from the ſerpent, and how he may be ſaid to be a lier. p. 3.</item>
               <item>3. Proved from the effects of the fruit, or opening of the eyes, and what theſe eyes are. p. 4. 5.</item>
               <item>4. Proved from God himſelf. p. 6. 7.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Object.</hi> that ſaith that God ſpeaketh by way of an Irony, anſwered. p. 7. 8.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Object.</hi> that ſaith <hi>Adam</hi> knew good by the loſſe of it, and evil by wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:169878:7"/>
anſwered. p. 9.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Object.</hi> that ſaith <hi>Adam</hi> was made in the image of God, anſwered thus. p. 10.</item>
               <item>The image of God is underſtood two wayes, 1. his perſonal appearance, 2. his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and immortal ſubſtance. ibid.</item>
               <item>Adam was made after the image of Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and how. p. 11.</item>
               <item>The woman was not made after the image of God, in the firſt ſence, proved. p. 12. 13, 14.</item>
               <item>The ſecond Image deſcribed, and how the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> may be ſaid to be made after it in the firſt. p. 15. 16.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Object.</hi> and Reaſon given that ſaith <hi>Adam</hi> was not made in the ſecond image, anſwered. p. 17. 18.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>To confirm the propoſition.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>1. Reaſon; That which is immortal cannot become mortal. p. 19.</item>
               <item>A query what they mean by holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, if naturall, or if without ſin, anſwered. p. 20.</item>
               <item>What the true image is. ibid.</item>
               <item>2. Reaſon, <hi>Adam</hi> was made carnal and earthly, proved by Scripture and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. p. 21. 22.</item>
               <item>3. Reaſon, As the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was always one and the ſame, ſo was the firſt. <hi>Object.</hi> anſwered. p. 23. 24.</item>
               <item>4. Reaſon, Our firſt parents had original
<pb facs="tcp:169878:7"/>
ſin, before they eat of the forbidden fruit. p. 25. 26.</item>
               <item>Sin deſcribed two ways. p. 27.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Object.</hi> that ſaith, ſin was begotten by the Serpent, anſwered. p. 28.</item>
               <item>Sin in them before they eat, by the oppoſers confeſſion. p. 29.</item>
               <item>The ground of this contradiction dicove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. p. 30.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Object.</hi> from regeneration, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. p. 31. 32.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Object.</hi> from the tranſgreſſion, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. p. 43, 44. 46.</item>
               <item>What <hi>Adam</hi> is in the ſubſtance. p. 35. 36.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Appli. Adams</hi> eſtate laid down, and ours compared with his in ſeven degrees. p. 37.</item>
               <item>1. <hi>Adam</hi> is made out of Paradiſe, and ſo are we. 38.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Adam</hi> is put into paradiſe, and ſo are we, p. 39.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Adam</hi> was to till the ground and to eat of every tree but one, and ſo are we p. 39.</item>
               <item>4. Our firſt Parents did deſire to eat of the forbidden fruit, to become like God, and ſo do we p. 40, 41, 42.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Obj.</hi> from the breach of the command, anſwered p. 43, 44, 45.</item>
               <item>The tree of Life is the righteouſneſſe of God, proved by ſcripture and 4 reaſons, p. 46, 47</item>
               <item>And ſo conſequently the tree of knowledg of
<pb facs="tcp:169878:8"/>
good &amp; evil, is the righteouſnes of man, ib.</item>
               <item>5. He eateth of that fruit, and ſo do we, p. 48</item>
               <item>What is meant by eating, explained, p. 49,</item>
               <item>What is ſin, or what is ſin after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion p. 50, 51, 52.</item>
               <item>7 Things effected and brought forth upon <hi>Adam</hi> by his eating, anſwerable to the like 7. in us by our eating p. 53.</item>
               <item>1. He is deprived of life, and ſo are we, p. 54</item>
               <item>2. It diſcovers ſin both to him and us, p. 54</item>
               <item>3. It brings fear both upon him and alſo to us p. 55.</item>
               <item>4. It brings a curſe upon both p. 56, 57</item>
               <item>5. It brings death it ſelf to both, p. 58</item>
               <item>None dyed in that fleſh of his, but every one doth dye in and for himſelf; what ſeems to be truth at one time, may not be truth after further light, p. 59, 60, 61, 62</item>
               <item>6. It cauſed him to cloath himſelf with fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leafs, and ſo it doth to us, p. 63</item>
               <item>Theſe fig-leafs, and the leafs of the tree of life deſcribed, p. 64, 65</item>
               <item>7. The eating of the fruit, did cauſe him to run away from God, and hide himſelf in the tree of the Garden; ſo it doth to us: the Tree deſcribed, p. 66, 67</item>
               <item>An Objection anſwered, p. 68</item>
               <item>The 6 degree of <hi>Adams</hi> riſing; he is cloathed with Skins, and ſo are we p. 69, 70</item>
               <item>What theſe Skins are; and how, and when
<pb facs="tcp:169878:8"/>
we are cloathed with them, p. 71, 72, 73</item>
               <item>An Objection anſwered, how the firſt diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is of God, and how not, p. 75, 76</item>
               <item>The ſecond is of God in a more peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, p. 77</item>
               <item>The myſtery of the Trinity opened, p. 78, 79, 80</item>
               <item>7. Adam is caſt out of paradiſe, and ſo are we: all diſpenſations give way to this, p. 81, 82, 83</item>
               <item>We are brought into a ſecond paradiſe, </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe. Firſt, this teacheth us to be reconciled to God p. 84</item>
               <item>Secondly, a word of reconciliation to ſeven ſorts of men, p. 85, 86, 87, 88, 89</item>
               <item>The ſtrong brother and the weak ought not to condemn nor judg one another, p. 90, 91, 92</item>
               <item>It is Antichriſtian, and of the Devill to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell one another to any thing in matter of worſhip; which is contrary to the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, p. 92, 93</item>
               <item>All ought to walk according as they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, p. 94</item>
               <item>An Objection anſwered, p. 95, 96</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:169878:9"/>
            <l>REader behold Jewels and Pearles her ſet,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Jaſper</hi> and <hi>Amethiſts</hi> in this rich Cabinet;</l>
            <l>Behold the way if thou theſe Pearls wilt find,</l>
            <l>From ſtep to ſtep unto this glorious mine,</l>
            <l>Three ways there are to ſee this heavenly place,</l>
            <l>Through a vail, a glaſs, and after face to face;</l>
            <l>The Earth ſhall ſhake, and alſo Heav'n above,</l>
            <l>That thoſe things may remain, which ſhall ne'remove;</l>
            <l>Though ADAM did aſpire on high by Earth,</l>
            <l>Yet fall he did, and loſt his prize through death,</l>
            <l>That unto life be might be brought again,</l>
            <l>And ſo at laſt his firſt prize might obtain;</l>
            <l>He's cloath'd with skins, a glorious cloathing then,</l>
            <l>None ſuch are found amongſt the Sons of men.</l>
            <l>Thus may you learn throughout this Hiſtory,</l>
            <l>Degrees of grace working men up to glory.</l>
            <l>Therefore let all men reſt in this contented,</l>
            <l>For they in ADAM are all repreſented;</l>
            <l>And firſt as be began to play the prize,</l>
            <l>So we as he muſt die before we riſe.</l>
            <byline>By W. R.</byline>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169878:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ADAM</hi> UNVAYLED, AND <hi>Seen with open Face.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Principle which I doe here oppoſe and deny to be a Truth, is this as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IT is held almost by al thoſe profeſs the Chriſtian Religion; that</hi> Adam <hi>was made in the Image of God in righteouſneſs, wiſdom, and knowledge, and the like; and that by eating of the forbidden fruit be loſt that Image; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thoſe Attributes, in which he was ſaid to be made like unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is their underſtanding of <hi>Adam's</hi> eſtate, with whom I have to deal; others hold other things of <hi>Adam,</hi> although not ſo groſs or ſo far contrary to truth: and I not knowing fully what all opinions are, I ſhall lay down my own judgment, which is clear contrary to theirs; whoſe opinions are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpecified. According to my underſtanding, the Spirit of God holds forth in Scripture,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169878:10"/>
that the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was made of earth earthly,</p>
            <p>For he loſt nothing by his eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit; he having nothing to loſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſdom, righteouſneſs, knowledge, or light inherentin himſelf; but contrarily, being meerly blinde, fooliſh, ignorant, and empty of all thoſe attributes, which he was ſaid to have: and whereas it is ſaid that <hi>Adam</hi> loſt all thoſe attributes by eating the forbidden fruit; I ſay he gained all his naturall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, light, righteouſneſs, wiſedom, and the like, by vertue of his eating the forbidden fruit; And I make it appear thus: There were two ſpeciall Trees in <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> the one was the Tree of <hi>Knowledge, of good and evil;</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the Tree of <hi>Life;</hi> the fruit of theſe two Trees, was nothing elſe but two laws of righteouſneſs. The firſt, which was the Tree of <hi>Knowledge</hi> of good and evil, was the law of nature, which is the morall law, and is called the righteouſneſs of man. The ſecond Tree, was the Law of the Spirit and life in Chriſt, which is by gift, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the righteouſneſſe of God: now before <hi>Adam</hi> had eaten of either of theſe Trees, he could have neither of theſe two lawes of righteouſneſs, which he had not until he had eaten of the fruit thereof.</p>
            <p>For proof whereof, it will Firſt appear from the very attribute or title, that is put
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169878:10"/>
upon the Tree: it is called the Tree of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of good and evill; and the reaſon is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it gives &amp; conveys knowledge of what is good, and what is evil, in thoſe who eat it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It may be alſo proved from the <hi>Serpents</hi> teſtimony: he ſpeaking in anſwer<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. 4.</note> to the woman, when ſhe ſaid <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. that God had ſaid, <hi>ye ſhall not eate of it, neither ſhall you touch it leaſt you die:</hi> his anſwer was, <hi>ye ſhal not ſurely die;</hi> but contrarily ſaith he, <hi>God knoweth that in the day you cat thereof, your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods knowing good and evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But it may be ſome may ſay that the</hi> Serpent <hi>did lye, and deceive</hi> Eve <hi>by theſe words. and therefore is called a lier from the begining.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Serpent</hi> ſpake truth according to the womans ſenſe and interpretation of death, that was the diſſolution of the body, but not according to Gods meaning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of death: therefore he is called a lyer from the begining, as in another cauſe. Although the witneſsſes did teſtifie againſt Chriſt <hi>Matth</hi> 26 61. And likewiſe againſt <hi>Steven, Act.</hi> 6. 13. Although theſe witneſſes ſpeak nothing but truth, as it appears, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 19. compared with <hi>Math.</hi> 26. 61. and alſo <hi>Steven</hi> denies not what was teſtified againſt him; and proves it by <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 33. 48. Yet for all this, thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169878:11"/>
two ſorts of witneſſes are called falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, inaſmuch as they did not ſpeak ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their meaning; and in this ſenſe the <hi>Serpent</hi> is called a lyer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; becauſe he ſpeakes not according to Gods meaning of death.</p>
            <p>But he was not a lyer according to the womans ſenſe or interpretation of death; which was the diſſolution of the body; for they did eate that day, but did not die a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall death: thus it is alſo proved from the <hi>Serpent</hi>'s teſtimony: that their eyes ſhall be opened, and they ſhall become like Gods knowing good and evill.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It will appear to be a truth from the effects that the fruit did work on them, by which the <hi>Serpent</hi>'s words to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is made good, <hi>verſ. 6. 7. And when the woman ſaw the Tree was good for food, and pleaſant to the oye, and a Tree to be deſired to make one wiſe; ſhe took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave alſo unto her huſband with her, and he did eat. And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew they were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked:</hi> Thoſe eyes were not mortal, or ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial eyes of the body; for they were open to ſee the fruit before they eat thereof: <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. what eyes are there elſe to be opened beſides the mortal eyes of the body? there are two ſorts of eyes beſides the mortal eyes of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169878:11"/>
body: the firſt is the natural eyes, and the ſecond is the ſpiritual eyes; and as I told you before, there was two ſorts of fruits to open theſe two ſorts of eyes: and here you may ſee upon eating the firſt ſort of fruit, the firſt ſort of eyes were opened, namely the eyes of their natural knowledge, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and underſtanding; for the text ſaith, <hi>and they knew that they were naked;</hi> it doth not ſay it made them naked, for they were ſo before; but before they eat, they had not that underſtanding to know that they were naked, or be aſhamed of their nakedneſſe: but by vertue of their eating of that fruit there was knowledge, and wiſdom, and light conveyed into them, whereby they knew what was good and what was evill; therefore well might it be called the Tree of Knowledge of good and evill, when it hath ſuch vertue in it to give knowledge, which could not be attained unto any other wayes, as it may be neceſſarily gathered by that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe between God and <hi>Adam,</hi> when <hi>the Lord called to Adam, and ſaid, where art thou? veſ.</hi> 9. Adam's anſwer was, <hi>I heard thy voice in the garden and I was afraid becauſe I was naked, verſ.</hi> 10. Gods anſwer to him again was, <hi>who told thee that thou waſt naked? haſt thou eaten of the Tree whereof I command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee thou ſhouldſt not eat?</hi> as much as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169878:12"/>
if God had ſaid, it is true thou art naked, (he denyes it not) but it is impoſſible that thou ſhouldeſt know of it, without thou waſt told, becauſe thou haſt no knowledge in thy ſelf, except thou haſt eaten of the forbidden fruit: this ſpeech of God is as if a man ſhould determine in himſelf to doe ſome good for his ſon, and yet make it known but to one man in the world; and yet the ſon ſhall come to his father, and ſay, if you would doe ſuch a thing for me; his father knowing that none knew it but one, will ſay, who told thee? haſt thou ſpoken with ſuch a man, implying that he did give his ſon knowledge of ſuch a thing, without which he could not know. No more could <hi>Adam</hi> know his nakedneſs, which indeed was his earthlineſs, without he had eaten of that Tree as it is clear from theſe words) <hi>who told thee that thou waſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked? haſt thou eaten of the Tree, whereof I commanded thee that thou ſhouldſt not eat?</hi> Here you ſee opening of eyes, and diſcovery of nakedneſs effected in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> by their eating the forbidden fruit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We ſhall confirm all theſe, and put the point out of queſtion from God himſelf, where the ſaith, <hi>behold the man is become as one of us, knowing good and evil, Chap. 3. verſ.</hi> 22. If <hi>Adam</hi> by his eating
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169878:12"/>
the forbidden fruit became like God, then it will follow that he was not like God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Adam</hi> by his eating of the fruit of the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came like God in the knowledge of good &amp; evil: that is, what God eſteemed to be good, that <hi>Adam</hi> knew, and eſteemed likewiſe to be good; and what God eſteemed to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that <hi>Adam</hi> alſo knew and eſteemed to be evil: although <hi>Adam</hi> did not know things in that meaſure and fulneſs as God did; yet he knew as God did, in the ſame manner, or nature; as a coale is like a whole world ſet on fire, ſo was <hi>Adam</hi> like God in the knowledge of good and evil; but here lies <hi>Adam</hi>'s miſery in knowing good and evil, and yet not having power to do the good known, and ſhun the evil; which could not be obtained by the eating this fruit, but by the eating of the ſecond fruit, which is of the Tree of life, as I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhew; I might further confirm this truth by divers arguments and reaſons; but before I proceed, it is neceſſary that I ſhould anſwer divers objections which lie in the way.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>You will ſay, it is true God ſaith,</hi> the man is become like one of us; <hi>but God ſpeakes by the way of an Ironye; as</hi> Micaiah
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169878:13"/>
               <hi>ſpeakes to</hi> Ahab, the 1 of Kings 22. 15. <hi>the King asked him whether he ſhould go up to</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth-Gilead <hi>to battle or no? The Prophet</hi> Micaiah <hi>bids him,</hi> go up, and proſper; and the Lord ſhall deliver it into the hands of the King. <hi>So God ſpeakes to</hi> Adam, <hi>becauſe of his former high thoughts, and indeavours to be great; and when Adam fell ſhort of what he thought to be, God ſpeaks to him in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> God ſpeakes not in the way of an Irony: my reaſons are theſe; firſt, becauſe God ſpeakes not to <hi>Adam</hi> as the Prophet did to <hi>Ahab,</hi> or as the wiſe man in the Proverbs did to the young man. But God ſpeaks to himſelf, in reſpect of his threefold relation; that is either like God in his eternal eſſence or being; or like God in reſpect of his influence and power: or thirdly like him as he dwelleth and acteth, and abaſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Chriſt; or rather like him in the knowledge of good and evil, according as he eſteems good and evil, in either of theſe relations; therefore I ſay, God ſpeaking to the <hi>Trinitie,</hi> and not to <hi>Adam;</hi> It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for God to ſpeake in the way of an Irony, or deriding, or rather blaſphemy, becauſe he ſpeakes not to the perſon offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Prophet did: therefore your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will not ſerve, the caſe being not the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169878:13"/>
ſame; if God had ſpoken to <hi>Adam,</hi> there might have been ſome ſhow or colour for ſuch a thing; but God ſpeaking not to him, there can be no ground or colour for it at all.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon is, why God ſpeaks, not in the way of an Irony is this: becauſe there was ſome thing enacted upon, and by reaſon of his knowledge, in the latter part of the 22. 23. <hi>verſes: and now leaſt he take of the tree of life and live for ever:</hi> as much as if God<note place="margin">It was the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God in <hi>Adam</hi> that drove him out of the garden <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 24.</note> had ſaid, he is come to that knowledge by vertue of his eating the fruit, he wil be ready to take of the tree of life and live for ever: It is clear that <hi>Adam</hi> was put forth by reaſon of his knowledge; therefore the Lord God ſent him forth from the garden of <hi>Eden;</hi> the word <hi>therefore,</hi> hath ſome dependance upon the fore going words, which was his becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like God; therefore he was driven forth.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon proves it a truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the former 3 proofs. Firſt from the name of the tree, Secondly from the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents teſtimony, and Thirdly from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that the fruit produced in them; all with ſpeaking one thing, it doth further confirm that Gods meaning was really ſo according as it was ſpoke, behold the man is become like one of us, knowing good &amp; evil.</p>
            <p>2 Object. <hi>And that is from the latter part of the verſe, knowing good and evil; it is true,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169878:14"/>
Adam <hi>knew good and evill; but how? he knew good by the loſſe of it, and evill by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſhall grant, if God knew good by the loſſe of it, and evill by wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then <hi>Adam</hi> did ſo to; But if God did not, then <hi>Adam</hi> did not neither; for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> knew good and evill as God did, and ſo ſaith the text, <hi>Behold the man is become libe one of us knowing good and evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>You will ſay</hi> Adam <hi>was made in the image of God as the Scripture holdeth forth, and he being in the image of God in reſpect of his attributes before his eating the forbidden fruit; therefore it followeth he became not like God by his eating as you do here affirm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer to this <hi>Objection,</hi> you muſt underſtand that the image of God is held forth in Scripture under a two-fold conſideration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The image of his perſon or viſible appearance, Secondly, The image of his incomprehenſible and ſpirituall ſubſtance. Now as you underſtand <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency as meer man, he was made after the firſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that is to ſay in the image of God in reſpect of his perſon or viſible appearance, and not after the ſecond image, although he was in ſome ſenſe, in reſpect of God, as I ſhall hereafter ſhew when I come to ſpeak
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169878:14"/>
of the ſecond image; but when I ſay <hi>Adam</hi> was made in the image of God in reſpect of his perſon or viſible appearance, we are not to underſtand that God in his eternall Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and being can be likened to any thing; for he is inviſible and incomprehenſible, but I meane in that ſhape and likeneſſe as God did alwayes appear and manifeſt himſelf in unto the ſons of men, before the law to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and in the time of the Law, and alſo in the fulnes of time, in the fleſh of a man, even in the man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> for God in his eternall thought and purpoſe beforetime did determine and intend (as he did in other things) to appear in this image in time, and ſo called it his image; &amp; likewiſe in his determination intended to make man according to it; and one end was to ſpeak according to mans capacitity; for if God had appeared in other ſhapes, and not in the ſhape or likneſſe of man, then man through feare would not be capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a meſſage or be inſtructed by him (man being in that weak eſtate as he is made in) ſo God in time made man according to the ſhape or image which he intended to appear in before time; And when he ſaith, let us make man in our own image: his meaning is in the firſt ſenſe, that mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhoul be made like the image of Gods
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169878:15"/>
perſon or viſible appearance, according as I have already deſcribed. It muſt needs be ſo for this reaſon; becauſe the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was not made in the image of God: now if you underſtand by <hi>image</hi> any thing beſides the image of his perſon or viſible appearance, let it be knowledge, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wiſdom or what it will, in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, the man and the woman was both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; but if I ſhall prove the woman was not made like the man in the image of God; then it muſt needs be granted that the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage that <hi>Adam</hi> was made like unto God in, was the image of his perſon or viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble appearance. To the end the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in proving that man was made in the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, and the woman was not, take notice what followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It will appear from Gods reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before mans creation, as you may ſee <hi>Geneſis</hi> 1 26. where God ſaith, let us make man in our own image: the woman is not mentioned, neither yet included in the man, as it appears in the 27. <hi>verſe;</hi> where you ſhall find a particular relation; Firſt, how the man was created in theſe words; <hi>So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him:</hi> Secondly, that they were both created in the latter part of the <hi>verſe</hi> in theſe words, <hi>male and female crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169878:15"/>
he them;</hi> the ſame expreſſion is in <hi>Gen. chap. 5. verſ.</hi> 2. from hence it doth cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear that the man was created in the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, and the woman was not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a particular relation of their creation; for if they had been both created in the image of God, it had been eaſier to ſay in the image of God created he them male and female, then to particulariſe out the man, and ſay he was created in the image of God, &amp; then go over them again, and ſay male &amp; female created he them; ſo that by this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular relation the Holy Ghoſt would have us to underſtand, that the man was created after the image of God, but not the woman; the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> by the ſame ſpirit clearly underſtands this truth, and puts it out of controverſie; he ſpeaking in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 7. how a man ought to manifeſt his obedience and ſubjection (to his head, which is God) by his being uncovered either in prayer or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying; and alſo how a woman ought to manifeſt her ſubjection to her head by her being covered; he ſaith if the woman be not covered, let her be ſhaven or ſhorn; and as he looks upon it to be a great evil in the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be uncovered; ſo contrarily he looks upon it to be a great evil in the man to be covered; and his reaſon's this, for ſaith he, a man indeed ought not to cover his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169878:16"/>
head, for as much as he is the image and gory of God: now obſerve, if that be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon why he ought not to be covered, becauſe he is the image of God; I ſay by the ſame reaſon the woman ought not to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, if ſhe had been the image of God; but ſhe being not the image of God, but the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the man, therefore ſhe ought to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; I ſay again, if they that be in the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, do diſhonour God by being covered, in praying or propheſying, as it appears they do by the Apoſtles reaſon: then <hi>Paul</hi> commands the women of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to diſhonour God, if they were made in the image of God; but they being not in the image of God, therefore did not diſhonour God, but by it honoured their husbands; further, to prove that the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was not made in the image of God, ſpoken of in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the image there mentioned muſt needs be a perſonal image.</p>
            <p>My ſecond reaſon is this; becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> as they were made viſible and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſubſtances, they were both Typicall of two ſeveral things; <hi>Adam</hi> typed out Chriſt the ſecond man, and <hi>Eve</hi> the Church: and as the things typed out were of two ſeveral natures or figures; it muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the types themſelves muſt be of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169878:16"/>
two natures or figures: this muſt needs be ſo for this reaſon, becauſe the woman and the man is not alike in reſpect of their natural image neither in ſhape, ſtrength, or govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: therefore Gods meaning muſt needs be underſtood of mans perſonal image to be made like Gods.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon may be this, becauſe God alwayes appeared in the ſhape of a man, and not in the ſhape of a woman. Thus having proved that the woman was not made in the image of God, it wil therefore neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the image ſpoken of was a perſonal &amp; viſible image, &amp; not the image of God in reſpect of holineſs, righteouſneſs, wiſdom, or the like; for you ſay, and I grant, that the man and woman are both alike in that; but you ſee they were not both alike in the image of God; for <hi>Adam</hi> was made in the image of God, and <hi>Eve</hi> was not, which is already proved; thus you ſee the image of God is taken for the image of his perſon, or viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the firſt ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The image of God is held forth<note place="margin">A ful anſwer to the <hi>Objecti page</hi> 1 c</note> under a ſecond conſideration, and in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining this, I ſhall further clear that which is already delivered. And this ſecond i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is the inviſible, incomprehenſible, and immortall image; it may be taken, and is underſtood, as I have already declared, thus:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169878:17"/>
let us make mans perſon after the image of Gods perſon; but God reſted not here, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would he have us to reſt here: but look through the ſhadow to the ſubſtance, through the viſible and perſonal image, to the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, incomprehenſible, &amp; immortal image; through the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> to the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> God ſpeakes after the manner of men, in darke ſhadows and parables, and carnal men underſtand accordingly, when indeed God lookes through theſe ſhadows and means a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing; God ſaith, let us make man; here he ſpeakes after the manner of man becauſe a man is a man to men; but to God<note place="margin">* Carnal.</note> man is not man, but a meer bubble or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: therefore God lookes upon man in his own account; and his meaning is, let us make the new ſubſtantial and immortal <hi>Adam,</hi> after the incomprehenſible and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal image; this ſaying of God muſt needs be underſtood as that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. 13. When <hi>Noah</hi> came out of the Arke, <hi>he took of every clean beaſt, and offered burnt offerings;</hi> and the text ſaith that <hi>the Lord ſmelled a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and the Lord ſaid in his heart, I will not again curſe the earth any more for mans ſake.</hi> Could a company of poor earthly creatures make a ſweet ſmelling ſavour in the noſtrils of God; no, no, God looks through theſe carnal and typical offerings, to the ſpiritual
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169878:17"/>
and Antitypical offerings; which are the ſweet breathings, and carryings forth of the ſpirits of the Saints upon the Altar, which is the divine nature of Chriſt, to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and fellowſhip with himſelf: So in the like manner, when God ſaith <hi>let us make man,</hi> he lookes through the carnal man, to the ſpiritual and true man, who is created after the image of God, in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs &amp; true holineſs: and therefore Chriſt<note place="margin">In this image male and female all one in Chriſt.</note> is ſaid to be the expreſs image of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; we are not to underſtand that he means that Chriſt is the expreſs image of his viſible perſon; that perſon which was ſpoken of 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 11. 7. in which the woman was not made in, as it hath been made appear: but he means that inviſible and immortal righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and holineſs which is in God, in his eternal eſſence and being. This word <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> is a phraſe after the manner of men, to ſet out inviſible and incomprehenſible things by that which is viſible; it is called the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe image of his perſon, in oppoſition to all other typical images, or outward fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate holinſs or righteouſneſs whatſoever; this is the true image, and new man, that the Saints are to put on, in oppoſition to the falſe image and old man which muſt be put off.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Some may ſay Gods meaning could not be of this immortall, inviſible, or ſecond image
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169878:18"/>
which God ſpeaks of, when he ſaith</hi> let us make man, <hi>becauſe this image was not then made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Saints are ſaid to be choſen in Chriſt, before the foundation of the world; if choſen, then made under the ſame conſideration; for things muſt be before they can be choſen. Again men may ſay, let us make a houſe, and in order thereunto make morter, and bricke; and in doing that, they may be ſaid to make the houſe: So it may be underſtood of God in this place, It was Gods great end to bring up the elect who were choſen before the foundation of the world into a communion and fellowſhip with himſelf; And in order to this he makes the perſon or outward tabernacle for this new man to dwell in, and to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this great end (that is to ſay) to make man in his owne immortall and ſubſtantiall Image; for in making the outword and perſonall hee may be ſaid to make the outward: and Spirituall, for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>How be it that was not firſt which was ſpirituall, but that which was carnall, and afterwards that which was ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 46. Therefore when God ſaith let us make man, he looks through the firſt to the latter, and meanes the end of things, this is that new man, a man in Gods own account. I having deſcribed the image of God under theſe two conſiderations and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169878:18"/>
withall proved that <hi>Adam</hi> as he was in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency was made after the firſt image, that is to ſay, the image of his perſon; I ſhall alſo go on in proving that <hi>Adam</hi> as he was then made and ſtood in innocency, was not made after the ſecond image in holineſſe, righteouſneſſe, knowledge, and the like; and my reaſons are theſe;</p>
            <p>Firſt. If <hi>Adam</hi> had been immortall in the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1.</note> of God, in reſpect of his attributes, it had been as impoſſible for him to fall and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mortal, and unholy, as it would be for God himſelf; that which is holy, cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unholy; that which is in the nature of God, cannot change it nature into the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſin: God is able to change other things into his nature; but no other thing can change that which is of God into its nature. Becauſe I would leave nothing unanſwered,</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>I would willingly know what you meane by holineſs and righteouſneſs: if you mean natural holineſs and righteouſneſs, knowledge, light, and the like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer, God hath no ſuch image: the Scripture holds forth but a twofold Image; the firſt a Perſonal, the ſecond a Spiritual, according as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready deſcribed.</p>
            <p>Again, If you ſay, he was holy and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, inaſmuch as he had not ſinned; I ſay,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169878:19"/>
in that ſenſe, a ſtone, or any other vegetative or ſenſitive creature is made in the image of God, for it hath not ſinned: This is like that tenet or principle held concerning chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: for ſome ſay, If children ſhould not be ſaved, who have never ſinned actually, who then can be ſaved? as if that which had not ſinned, was holy and nearer God: to be without ſin only, is not to be holy, and in the image of God; or to have never ſo much naturall knowledge and light adds nothing to holineſs and righteouſneſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods image: But to be holy and righteous in the image of God, is to be immortall, unchangeable, and to have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life in them, which is the gift of God, and there to live in the enjoyment of God, having inherent righteouſneſs in them; and to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be begotten by God, and grow up in the very nature of God, as a child grows up in the nature of his Father: So that you muſt become little children, and be born by the Spirit, before you enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven: that is, there muſt be a new and ſecond birth of a new creature, a new life and converſation, new feeding, new ſpirituall meat, and drinking anew of wine and water of life with Chriſt in the Father's kingdom, a new enjoyment, a new ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reſt, and all things muſt become new<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169878:19"/>
all this is held forth by the firſt birth, life, converſation, feeding and reſting. If we muſt become like (or, <hi>as</hi>) little children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can enter into the Kingdom of heaven; then I ſay, we muſt become like old men before we ſit down in the Kingdom of heaven in the full enjoyment of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or in the knowledge of him which is from the beginning, as the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith to the Fathers, who out-ſtripped the children or young men in the knowledge of God, as he was in them from the beginning, 2 <hi>John</hi> 12, 14. Theſe children are not to be underſtood children by generation; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the young men or fathers to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood under a natural conſideration; but children in reſpect of regeneration, and young men and fathers in reſpect of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all growth, and knowledge in the myſtery of God.</p>
            <p>So then, if <hi>Adam</hi> had been thus, he had been in the image of God, and could no more have fallen away from the nature and image of his Father, then a childe can fall from the nature and image of his father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the nature and image of a beaſt: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he fall in that ſenſe, as you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand he did, nor do any thing againſt, or contrary to his nature.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He was earthly, and ſo he acted<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169878:20"/>
from that principle, and therefore not in the image of God: and that you may plainly ſee, if you conſider what the Apoſtle ſaith 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 43. in theſe words, <hi>There is a carnall body, and there is a ſpirituall body.</hi> Although this may be taken or underſtood to be our body, or the body of ſin fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> in oppoſition to the ſpirituall body, which is the ſpirit of life in Chriſt; yet it is not the Apoſtles underſtanding onely; for he goes about to prove this by the written word; and that is from <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for (ſaith he) and ſo it is written <hi>The firſt man Adam was made a living ſoul, the laſt Adam was made a quickning ſpirit, 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 45. The Apoſtle underſtands this firſt man that was made a living ſoul, to be a meer natural man; as alſo he underſtands the ſecond to be a ſpirituall, as you may ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 46. in theſe words, <hi>Howbeit, that was not firſt which was ſpirituall, but that which was carnall, and afterwards that which was ſpirituall.</hi> There needs no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evidence in this, neither can I ſpeak any plainer then the Apoſtle; for when he goes to prove there is a naturall bodie, he doth not ſay it became naturall through ſome miſcarriage; but he ſaith, he was made ſo: he was made a living ſoul, which living ſoul ſo made by God, he ſaith in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169878:20"/>
next verſe, that it was not ſpirituall, but carnal. Nothing that is carnall can have communion with God: But <hi>Adam</hi> was carnall: Therefore could have no commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God. Nothing that was made carnall was in the image of God: But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was made carnall: Therefore not in the image of God in reſpect of his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Apoſtle ſets forth the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degree<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or root of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> by the pedegree or root of the firſt, in theſe words; <hi>The firſt man is of the earth earthly, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond man is the Lord from heaven,</hi> verſ. 47. As the ſecond did not come in a low eſtate and condition, and attain to an higher af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; for he is the Lord from heaven: ſo the firſt man did not come in an high and glorious condition, and afterwards fall into a lower.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If you ſaid, That Chriſt, which is the ſecond man, came in a low eſtate and condition: which makes againſt this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, In reſpect of his Manhood he was the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> for it is ſaid, <hi>He that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified, are all of one.</hi> It is not onely meant in reſpect of their ſpirituall eſtates after they were ſanctified, but alſo of their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169878:21"/>
fleſhly, except actual ſin, as it is <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Foraſmuch as the Children are partakers of fleſh and blood, he alſo himſelf likewiſe took part of the ſame:</hi> And as he was fleſh and blood, he came in a low condition, and ſo he may be ſaid to grow in grace and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for he was not the Lord from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nor the ſecond man in this ſenſe; but he was the Lord from heaven in reſpect of his Godhead, or that ſpiritual influence or annoynting that came forth from God, and took up fleſh, and dewlt therein. In this ſenſe he was the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> which is the Lord from heaven; and as the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was alway the ſame, neither higher nor low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at any time; although he may be higher ſometimes, and ſometimes lower in reſpect of manifeſtation, yet he is one and the ſame for ever in his own nature and property: ſo alſo the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> might ſeem to be in a very high and good condition, and afterwards to be in a low and evill conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in reſpect of manifeſtation to himſelf, but in his own nature one and the ſame for ever; for he was made of the earth earthly: that is, Firſt, as his corporal ſubſtance was made of the materiall earth: ſo ſecondly, his eſtate and enjoyment was carnall and earthly; and being earthly minded, carnal, and blind, he was put into Paradiſe, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169878:21"/>
there continued untill his eyes were opened by his eating the tree of knowledge of good and evill; and then he had a diſcovery of his carnality, as I have already ſhewed in the letter, and ſhall hereafter open the myſtery to you, when I come to Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Further, if I can prove that our firſt parents had original ſin before they did eat of the forbidden fruit, the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie will be ended, and you muſt grant my opinion to be a truth: Which I ſhall prove, as it followeth,</p>
            <p>2. That our firſt parents had original<note place="margin">Reaſon 4.</note> ſin in them, by reaſon of which they could not ſtand in that eſtate as they were in, but fall; And it will appear thus; ſin is to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood<note place="margin">That is, have their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> under a two-fold conſideration: the firſt may be called ſin in its conception, that is the luſt and earneſt deſire and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heart to do ſuch a thing to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie its own luſt; this is ſin in it ſelf, and that which God hates and abominates, this is that which Chriſt witneſſeth againſt; for ſaith he, <hi>I ſay unto you, that whoſoever look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon a woman to luſt after her, hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted adultery already with her in his heart, Math. 5. verſ.</hi> 28. he ſaith alſo the ſame of murder, and other things <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. if it be conceived in the heart, its done in reſpect
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169878:22"/>
of God; for as God deſires and accepts of the good conceptions and indeavours of the heart, although they never be put into acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo rewards them: ſo he abhoreth the evill conceptions and intentions of the heart, and accounts it for ſin though it be never put into action, and rewards it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly if unrepented: thus I have deſcribed the firſt ſort of ſin, which indeed is ſin in it ſelf; and to ſpeak properly there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin but this, but that which I call the ſecond ſort of ſin, to ſpeak properly, is not ſin in its ſelf, but rather the manifeſtation of ſin, or ſin breaking forth and making it ſelf viſible; and this is called actuall ſin, which indeed is ſin to us: this is the ſecond ſort of ſin, or rather the manifeſtation of ſin; but that ſort of ſin or original corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is the body of ſin, this had <hi>Adam</hi> before he eat of the Tree of <hi>Knowldge of good and evill:</hi> to this purpoſe look into <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. where it is ſaid, firſt that ſhe ſaw it was good for food: and ſecondly, that it was pleaſant to the eye: and thirdly, it was a tree to be deſired to make one wiſ. All theſe three things conſidered by the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; the goodneſs of it, the pleaſantneſs of it, &amp; alſo that it would produce wiſdom: from hence it did cauſe luſt and a burning deſire in her after the fruit thereof; this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169878:22"/>
deſire and luſt was produced from that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſin, or original corruption and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ineſs within: and this ſin according to Chriſts expoſition <hi>Math.</hi> 5. is the ſin or traſgreſſion it ſelf; for their eating did not effect or produce their luſts and deſires, but their luſts and deſires did effect their taking the fruit and their eating thereof; and this was the ſin and tranſgreſſion it ſelf, as it is clear from the Apoſtles words, where he<note place="margin">I Tim. 2 14.</note> ſaith the man was not in the tranſgreſſion, but the woman; why ſo? did not the man eat of the forbidden fruit? yea he did eat of the fruit, but that was not the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; but the ſin or tranſgreſſion it ſelf was the deſire to the fruit, upon ſuch conſiderations as was before mentioned; and this deſire or luſt is recorded of <hi>Eve</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not of <hi>Adam,</hi> as the Apoſtle doth here affirm; now <hi>Eve</hi> holds forth the matter of the Church in this place, that is to ſay a carnal man and woman; and therefore the tranſgreſſions was attributed to her alone; (becauſe ſhe was the mother of all living, <hi>Gen. 3. verſ. 20.</hi>) And not to <hi>Adam,</hi> for <hi>Adam</hi> did type out Chriſt, and as he was a type he was paſſive in the tranſgreſſion, and carried away by <hi>Eve,</hi> and thus it is in the ſubſtance, <hi>Rom. 7. verſ. 23. but I ſee another</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169878:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169878:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169878:24"/>
               <hi>Law in my members warring againſt the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of my mind, and bringing me into captivity t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Law of ſin:</hi> but as <hi>Adam</hi> was a mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> creature, <hi>Eve</hi> held forth both him and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf, which is in the ſubſtance the carnal man and woman, or that part which quencheth the ſpirit, and carrieth away the inward man captive, as I ſhall further explain here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If it be ſaid that this deſire of</hi> Eve <hi>was begotten by, and through the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rpents tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This I do not deny, yet I ſay at this preſent it is ſo with us; for the Serpent doth ſet forth evill with all the advantage and ſhew of good as poſſibly he can; but all that he could doe either to <hi>Eve</hi> or us, is but to effect the body of ſin or original cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and malignity within, with the thing ſo ſet forth, (for he neither could give de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to them, nor yet to us) for the deſire was from ſome malignity or corruption with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; all that he could do was to make the evil appear lovely to the eye, that the deſire may be raiſed up after the ſame; as he hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things to work upon in us, ſo alſo he had in <hi>Eve,</hi> which was her corruption; if there had been nothing within her, he would have ſped with her as he did with Chriſt; for he having no fuel of original corruption, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169878:24"/>
the flame of the Serpents temptation could not kindle that which was not: but <hi>Eve</hi> having much power of original corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it was ſoon ſet on fire with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents temptation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, All thoſe that ſay <hi>Adam</hi> was<note place="margin">2. Proved from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> made in the Image of God in holineſs and righteouſneſs, do confeſs what is here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; namely, That our firſt parents had ſin and corruption before they ate of the fruit. It is a common ſaying both in their preaching and their writing, That <hi>Adam's</hi> aſpiring Pride and Ambition to become like God, was the cauſe of his Fall: Doctor<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> in his Book of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip. p. 11. Bifield</hi> in his <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, pag.</hi> 77, 80.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Adam</hi> rather obeyed the voice of the Serpent, then the voice of God. <hi>Bifield</hi> ſaith, There was three things occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the fall of our firſt parents; the firſt, Rebellion: the ſecond, Unthankfulneſſe: the third, Liberty they took to add or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from Gods word; they added the word <hi>touch,</hi> and they detracted when they ſaid, <hi>leſt ye die:</hi> And theſe three ſins are and ever will be cauſe of our Apoſtacie, ſaith he. Theſe are ſins in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as he himſelf confeſſeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 80. yet this was before they ate of the forbidden fruit, or the occaſion of it, as he ſaith. And thus they contradict themſelves, and give themſelves the lie; in that they ſay <hi>Adam</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169878:25"/>
was made in holineſs and righteouſneſs, and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Winſtanly</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts him ſelf in his Book of <hi>The myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God;</hi> compare <hi>pa.</hi> 1. with <hi>p.</hi> 10.</note> ſo continued till he ate of the fruit thereof; and yet to ſay, he ſinned before he ate thereof, this is a plain contradiction: and therefore the principle touching <hi>Adam's</hi> holineſs is not a truth. The ground of this contradiction is the miſunderſtanding of the Image of God: becauſe the Image of God is taken for holineſſe in the new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the new man, (according to that in <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3. 10.) therefore they attribute this holineſs and righteouſneſs to <hi>Adam</hi> in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, although they have no Scripture to prove it. Theſe two creations of man muſt be underſtood as theſe following things:</p>
            <p>The old Temple that was materiall, was a figure of the true, which is ſpiritual: the old Circumciſion made with hands, was a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the true made without hands: the old Sacrifices which were carnal, were a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the true, which are ſpirituall: So alſo the fleſhly and earthly birth which is ſeen, was a figure of the true birth which is ſpirituall, and not ſeen with mortall eyes, which is the new creation, or ſecond Image of God, in holineſs and righteouſneſs, the true Image of God in oppoſition to that perſonall and typical Image that <hi>Adam</hi> was made in: <hi>Except ye be born again, ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the Kingdom of heaven;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169878:25"/>
it is ſaid, <hi>again,</hi> yet the birth is not the ſame. So then, this being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Scripture, and alſo by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, That our firſt parents had originall ſin and corruption before they did eat of the forbidden fruit, which puts the queſtion out of controverſie, that is to ſay, that <hi>Adam</hi> was not made in the image of God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his attributes; neither had they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny power to ſtand in that condition as they were made, no more then a child hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſtay and never grow to be a man; and contrarily the ſame reaſon proves, that they were meerly blind, ignorant and carnal, whoſe enjoyment was altogether earthly, they being empty of all theſe attributes that they were ſaid to have.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>ſome may ſay that</hi> Adam <hi>was not mad in a low and carnal condition, and did by eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the forbidden fruit attaine to a higher, but contrarily he fell into a lower. Our reaſon is, becauſe the Scripture holds forth regeneration and renewing, which ſignifies our being brought up into ſome eſtate and condition that we were once in and now have loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This can be no reaſon againſt me, nor for you; for you your ſelves do not hold that we are by regeneration or the ſecond birth, brought up to that condition that we were in before in <hi>Adam;</hi> for if ſo, then we are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169878:26"/>
as liable to fall as ever. So then if we be not brought up to that eſtate that <hi>Adam</hi> was in, then regeneration is to be underſtood thus; we muſt be brought up in the like eſtate; now the like eſtate is not the ſame, but it it to be underſtood thus; as the lively creature is like the picture or repreſentation: ſo are regenerate perſons like <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency; for as he had peace, and enjoyment, and contentment, and was happy in his own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; ſo his carnal peace, delight, and enjoyment, was a figure of that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al peace, delight, and enjoyment, that is attained unto after the ſecond birth: For as he himſelf being carnal, was yet a figure of a heavenly and ſpirituall man; ſo alſo his enjoyment and peace, was a figure of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall peace and enjoyment; ſo, we are not to underſtand by regeneration that we are to be brought up into the ſame eſtate as <hi>Adam</hi> was in, but into the like eſtate, that is to ſay, into ſuch an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ate as his did hold forth, and was a figure of: for as the firſt eſtate was peace, contentments, &amp; delights; ſo is the ſecond, peace, contentments, and delights; and ſo may be ſaid to be like one a other, as a pictute of a creature is like the creature in reſemblance, yet not in life, power, and ſenſe; but as the one was peace, ſo was the other, and therein alike: the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169878:26"/>
Scripture holds forth a twofold birth, one like the other, and one holds forth the other; yet we muſt not be as <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve we are to enter into our mothers womb, becauſe Chriſt ſaith, we muſt be born again, or become like little children: And as this is to be underſtood in a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſenſe, that this ſpirituall birth is anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the naturall, and yet not the ſame; ſo is Regeneration to be underſtood in the like manner. Or elſe, as the reſtauration of Iſrael, and alſo their Ordinances, as it is ſaid in <hi>Amos 9 11. I will build up the tabernacle of David that is fallen, and cloſe up the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thereof, and I will raiſe up his ruines, and build it as in the dayes of old. And I will bring again the captivity of my people of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and they ſhall build Cities, and inhabit them,</hi> ver. 14. <hi>And I will plant them upon their own Land,</hi> ver. 15. Now, although theſe are plain words, as building a tabernacle as of old, and building Cities and planting them on their land; yet this muſt admit of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall interpretation, as it doth appear <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 16. where the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> applyeth this Propheſie to the calling of the Gentiles; and upon his repeating thereof in <hi>ver.</hi> 14, he draweth this inference, <hi>Therefore my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is that we trouble not them which from among the Gentiles are turned to God,</hi> ver. 19.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169878:27"/>
Theſe people thus turned to God, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands<note place="margin">This is the City of which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We are come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Mount Sion, the City of the living God, the heavenly Ieruſalem,</hi> Hebr. 12. 20. This is the City that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les ſhall tread un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot 42 months, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 2. The ſame ſpirituall City ſhall be redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 14. They ſhall call thee the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Lord, the Sion of the holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> One of Iſrael; that is, the Saints, and no materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al City.</note> to be the tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> in the ſubſtance thereof; and this their ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering in, and uniting by the Spirit is ſaid to be their building again as of old; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that of old was nothing but a tabernacle, or temple of wood or ſtone, with outward adornings of ſuch materiall things: as alſo the Cities and their own Land, which they are ſaid to build, and be planted in, are alſo ſpiritually held out by their old material Cities, as <hi>Sion, Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> which ſpirituall Cities are no material Cities, but ſuch Cities as righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhall be for walls and bulwarks: <hi>whoſe builder and maker is God, Iſa. 60. 18. Heb.</hi> 11. 10. Their own land there ſpoken of, is that heavenly and ſpirituall enjoyment and reſt which <hi>Joſhua</hi> could not bring them into, as you may ſee more plainly in the margin. Thus you are to underſtand Regeneration to be but only a bringing up to a ſpirituall peace and enjoyment, typed out by a carnall and earthly; God calleth in this place the things that are not, as though they were, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 17. he holds forth ſpirituall things by carnall, which are things we beſt underſtand: as in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> he holds out that excellent and ſpirituall love betwixt Chriſt and his Church, by that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169878:27"/>
love which is betwixt man and woman. Thus much in anſwer to this Objection.</p>
            <p>Another Objection may be formed thus:</p>
            <p>Some may ſay, <hi>Adam by his eating the fruit, did break a Commana, therefore it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that he could be brought neerer to God by his ſin and tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The matter of his eating was not ſin, but the manner or circumſtance, as you may ſee a full anſwer to this Objection in <hi>pag.</hi> 43, 44, 45, 46.</p>
            <p>I having briefly proved that which I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook, namely, that the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was made of the earth earthly, and was blinde, without wiſdom, knowledge, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, light, or the light, before his eating the forbidden fruit; and that he loſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by his eating, but by vertue thereof he obtained all thoſe naturall gifts which he is ſaid to have before, by them with whom I have to deal: and in proving of this, I having anſwered many Objections, Now it would be neceſſary to apply this truth to mens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall conditions; which indeed was Gods end in holding forth <hi>Adam</hi> in theſe various conditions, that we ſhould not onely ſee him, but ſee our ſelves: and in comparing our ſelves with <hi>Adam</hi> in his various condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and <hi>Adam</hi> with us, we may ſee our conditions like his: And herein I ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169878:28"/>
other Objections, and further clear what is already delivered.</p>
            <p>But before I come to apply this truth, you muſt know, that the man <hi>Adam</hi> did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent two things. 1. He did repreſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Adam,</hi> which is all the fleſhly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall actings of men in all the world: Theſe fleſhly and carnal actings of men, is <hi>Adam,</hi> as truly as ever he that was look'd upon to be our firſt parent was <hi>Adam:</hi> And God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt parent held forth Chriſt in the fleſh: <hi>Adam</hi> our carnality holds forth Chriſt in the Spirit; the firſt is crucified by the later, and gave place for grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound much more. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5 20.</note> was pleaſed to hold out this later <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> by him that is not ſo truly <hi>Adam</hi> as this; for this later <hi>Adam</hi> is he that we ſhould ſtill look to. And whereas I ſaid that <hi>Adam</hi> held forth two things, I did not mean only <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> our firſt parent, but this later <hi>Adam,</hi> our carnality holds forth the laſt of the two things which I ſpake of, which is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the Saints. The oppoſition is not between the two <hi>Adams;</hi> I mean <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt parent and Chriſt, who died at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> no further then they were two ſhadows: but the oppoſition lies between the two ſubſtances, namely, <hi>Adam</hi> our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality, and that ſpirit of life in Chriſt, living and acting in the Saints, which is the ſecond <hi>Adam:</hi> therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the old man, with the affections and luſts thereof, and put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:169878:28"/>
The ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom. 6. 6. Knowing this, that your old man is crucified with him:</hi> And in the next verſe he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what was done in the ſigne, that they might better judge and try themſelves whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had the ſubſtance in them anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the ſigne.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo as it doth appear, that every carnall man and woman, in their carnall, fleſhly, and ſelf actings, are the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 9, 10.</note> in the ſubſtance: Then let us ſee whether the ſame thing doth not befall us in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as befell <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſhadow, and ſo make ſome Application to our ſelves in our various conditions. And herein I ſhall ſtrengthen that which I have formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</p>
            <p>And in this I ſhall lay down <hi>Adams</hi> eſtate as he was created in, and his degrees in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through ſeverall diſpenſations and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of God, and ſo compare our eſtates and ſeverall degrees and riſings with his, and then we ſhall ſee whether he did not truly hold forth us, and whether we are not the true ſubſtance of him the ſhadow.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Adam</hi> was created without the<note place="margin">The firſt degree of <hi>Adam</hi>'s riſing.</note> Garden of <hi>Eden;</hi> which Garden holds forth a place of pleaſure and delight; ſo that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had not that pleaſure at his creation, but afterwards: and the reaſon was (as I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169878:29"/>
conceive) becauſe he was not capable of pleaſure, being created in the degree or ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a child. For he was not actually made by God (as ſome vainly and carnally ſuppoſe) but he grew out of ſome thing by the providence of God, and ſo was kept and provided for in a miraculous way by Gods great providence, as ſome men have been preſerved by Eagles and Bears, and the like, as is recorded in Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Divers Reaſons may be given for this; but I do not deſire to enlarge my ſelf in it: but take this one Reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> muſt needs be created in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or ſtature of a childe, becauſe he lived to the ſame age as his generation lived, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he departed this life, for his days were nine hundred and thirty yeers. Now if <hi>Adam</hi> had been in the degree of a middle aged man, in all probability he could not have lived to the age of the reſt of his generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for there was not above one in all his generation that did out-live him; which in all probability they would have done, if he had been created in the degree of a man.</p>
            <p>This I ſpeak from my ſelf, and not from the Lord; but there is much reaſon in it: Therefore you are not (in my judgment) to think, that God created him actually with hands, notwithſtanding it is ſaid that God
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169878:29"/>
formed man with the duſt of the earth: <hi>David</hi> ſaith the like of himſelf; <hi>Thy hands made and faſhioned me,</hi> notwithſtanding he came by generation. God made the whole world, but it was by his influence and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon and in the creature made, as he doth at this day; by the ſame power was <hi>Adam</hi> made, and kept by the ſame provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. And thus being made in the degree of a child without Paradiſe, that is to ſay, without pleaſure or delight, this was his firſt eſtate or degree. So it is with the ſubſtantiall <hi>Adam,</hi> which is all fleſh: in the time of their infancy they live without plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or delight, they being not yet capable of the ſame, being not yet put into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Eden.</hi> This is our firſt eſtate, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt eſtate.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Adam</hi> is put into the Garden<note place="margin">2. Degree of <hi>Adams</hi> riſing.</note> to till the ground; that is, into pleaſure and delight.</p>
            <p>The ſecond degree of the ſubſtantiall <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> thus anſwereth the ſecond degree of typicall <hi>Adam;</hi> who is likewiſe put into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, and grows up to be capable of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and delights, and to feed themſelves as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> did. There is no conſtraint in their natures; of every tree they may eat; that is, there is no command or power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in them, to debar or hinder them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169878:30"/>
from every fancy or delight which is in the garden of mans pleaſure; for the heart hath a freedom to feed on any thing that is preſented to the eye; which delights are held forth under the name of the trees of the Garden, according to the Metaphors held forth in <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek. 47. 12. Iſa. 55. 13.</hi> The thorn tree ſhall ſeem pleaſant to them.</note> Scripture; as you may ſee in the Margin.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They were to till the ground:<note place="margin">3 Degree of <hi>Adams</hi> riſing.</note> that is, they have knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to know what is good for nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to preſerve themſelves: As alſo it may be more properly underſtood by tilling the ground, their endeavouring to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves fit to receive good ſeed, as it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in <hi>Jerem. 4. 3. Break up the fallow</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 10. 12. Some are wrought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore others.</note> 
               <hi>ground, and ſow not among thorns.</hi> This is the condition from the age of ſix yeers and upwards upon all fleſh, before the creature be brought up to another degree.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Adam</hi> the type was prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from eating of one tree in the midſt of<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Degree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f <hi>Adams</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſing.</note> the Garden, upon the penalty of death: So in the like manner is <hi>Adam</hi> the antitype, which is all fleſh, prohibited from power in themſelves, and commanded in the word of God, not to go to make themſelves per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by their own righteouſneſſe, which is the tree of knowledge of good and evill in the ſubſtance; which tree, mans righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169878:30"/>
or the Law, is in the midſt of the garden, that is, of all the delights and ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters<note place="margin">The chief in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion.</note> that are: This is one of the chief, even placed in the very heart of man.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Adam</hi> the ſhadow had high and ambitious thoughts to be great, and did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to become like God by his own actings and endeavours, through the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of the Serpent, who ſo ſet forth the excellency of the fruit, and made it appear ſo lovely; (yet the Text ſaith, <hi>When</hi> ſhe <hi>ſaw it was good for food, and pleaſant to the eye, and a tree to be deſired, to make one wiſe, ſhe took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave unto her huſband with her, and he did eat:</hi> The taking of the fruit is here attributed to the woman only, and not unto the man; and the reaſon is, becauſe the woman held forth the Church, which is both man and woman: the man held forth Chriſt, and therefore he was not active in plucking the fruit, but <hi>Eve</hi> only was active in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. And although it be not proved that the man <hi>Adam</hi> did aſpire to be great; yet in as much as ſhe did, he did alſo in her; for all men and women were in her, and her name was <hi>Adam</hi> as well as his, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 2. this holds forth the myſtery of Chriſt and his Church, who aſſume each others names;) So then, it being cleer, that <hi>Adam</hi> the ſhadow
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169878:31"/>
was ambitious as a creature, and did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be great, and become like God; and to that end did pluck and eat of the forbidden fruit: It is alſo as clear, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> the ſubſtance, that is, all carnall men and women, do the ſame thing. When they are come through theſe three degrees, and are capable of any thing, they begin to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of the creation of the world, and to admire him that made all things. Thus it is naturall to all men (beſides being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by their parents) to meditate and learn to ſee the inviſible God in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure through the viſible things that are made. And thus their ſerious thoughts and conſiderations make them leave the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fruit in ſome meaſure, which is all manner of fancies, pleaſures, and delights, and begin to look into the middle of the garden, upon the fruit of the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and evill, which is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of man: and it is very pleaſant to the eye of carnall men: they cry out, This is the fruit that will make one wiſe, this is the food that we muſt eat in our journey to heaven: Thus mans righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is carnall mans food, or ſtrength by which he thinks to come to heaven. If you ask ſuch a man or woman how they think to be ſaved; they will ſay, by their good
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169878:31"/>
thoughts and works; and all the Gentiles (called Chriſtians) both Papiſts and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, do admire this fruit, which is mans righteouſneſs; and nothing elſe is ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the eye, to make one wiſe, or like God, or bring one to heaven, as this is in their apprehenſions.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, Mans righteouſneſs, which is<note place="margin">Here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins the Anſwer to the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>page</hi> 35.</note> the tree of knowldge of good and evill, was good to <hi>Adam,</hi> and is alſo to us: yet it was forbidden both to him, and alſo to us; that is, it was or is forbidden to accompliſh or bring about ſuch an end as man would have it do: that is to ſay, to become like God; although it doth ſo too in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in the knowledge of good and evill, as I have already ſhewed; yet it doth not in the performance of the thing known to be good, or the omitting of the thing known to be evill, or the living and the enjoying of that life and enjoyment that is in God; which ſhall not be obtained by the eating of the fruit of this tree, but by the eating of the fruit of the tree of life, which alſo is in the midſt of the Garden, and yet no naturall tree no more then the firſt: for this ſecond tree is Gods righteouſneſs, and the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaves of it ſhall ſerve for the healing of the Nations: ſo then, this firſt fruit is good in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts own place, and without the eating of this
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169878:32"/>
we cannot be capable of the other; yet it is forbidden to be eaten, to accompliſh the end that is before preſcribed, that is to ſay, to become like God.</p>
            <p>To prove this, take notice of theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and you ſhall finde this fruit, mans righteouſneſs is forbidden, and the ſentence of death paſſed on thoſe that feed on it to that end, as our firſt parents did: The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10. ſpeaks thus, <hi>For as many as are of the works of the law, are under the curſe. To be carnally minded is death,</hi> Rom. 8. 6. The Apoſtles meaning is, to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded in their comming up to God, or their ſeeking after God by or in carnall things, in endeavouring to make themſelves perfect by the fleſh, as they did to whom he ſpeaks <hi>Gal. 3. 3. Are you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o fooliſh, having begun in the ſpirit, are ye now made perfect by the fleſh?</hi> As alſo the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor. 13. 3. If</hi> he <hi>ſhould give his body to be burned, and all</hi> his <hi>goods to the poor, and have not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi> which is love, or the power of God living, and acting, and carrying him forth to do it, it is <hi>as ſounding braſſe, and a tinkling cymbal.</hi> The Prophets and Chriſt himſelf condemn Iſrael, or thoſe Pharifaicall men for their faſting, and making long prayers, <hi>Iſa. 58. 4. Matth.</hi> 6. 16. Why ſo? was it not good ſo to do? Yea, faſting, praying
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169878:32"/>
and giving of alms are good in themſelves;<note place="margin">So the things were good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or matter of them, but not in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; they may be uſed; but not fed on to be like God, leſt wee die.</note> but they had not the power of God carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out to do thoſe things, but the motive by which they were put upon thoſe duties was ſelf-ends, for to become like God: witneſſe the Phariſee that made the large confeſſion, and thought to obtain much, and yet was condemned by Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, as <hi>Adam</hi> was forbidden<note place="margin">Man is bidden, or command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do good, but not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain good by his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> to eat this fruit, and death pronounced, and a curſe followed upon his eating thereof: So in like manner are we forbidden to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after, or feed upon that fruit which is in the ſubſtance our righteouſnſs, or the Law, and alſo death is pronounced, and a curſe followeth upon our eating thereof; <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not, for all periſh</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adam</hi> did lie down in ſorrow.</note> 
               <hi>with the uſing,</hi> Col. 2. 21. This is the fire that man kindleth, and compaſſeth himſelf about with the ſparks: but God ſaith, <hi>This he ſhall have at mine hands, he ſhall lie down in ſorrow.</hi> So then here you ſee, that this ambition was not only in <hi>Adam</hi> the ſhadow, but in us the ſubſtance, after the forbidden fruit; and our ends are the ſame as his was, to be wiſe, and become like God, through the ſubtilty of the Serpent, which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169878:33"/>
holds forth the excellency of this fruit, our righteouſneſſe. This will alſo ſerve for an Anſwer to the Objection framed from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> tranſgreſſion, <hi>Pag.</hi> 35.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Some may ſay, How can the tree of knowledge of good and evill and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of man be all one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The fruit of the tree of knowledge of good and evill, is nothing elſe but the morall Law, or the righteouſneſs of man.</p>
            <p>It muſt needs be ſo for this Reaſon;</p>
            <p>Becauſe the other tree with it, which is the tree of life, was the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and no materiall or naturall tree.</p>
            <p>To prove that it was the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, you may ſee <hi>Rev. 2. 7. To him that overcometh will I give to eat of the tree of life in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God.</hi> The like is ſaid of the heavenly Manna, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. which is one and the ſame thing. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing promiſed to be given to the Saints to eat or to drink, or to be clothed with, but it is Chriſt or his righteouſneſs: He is all this to a Saint, as you may ſee in theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; He is <hi>water, John</hi> 4. 14. and <hi>chap. 7. 38. This he ſpake of the Spirit.</hi> He is <hi>Manna,</hi> chapt. 6. 48, 50. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 3. He is <hi>wine, pomegranats,</hi> or <hi>apples,</hi> or pleaſant fruit, <hi>Matth. 26. 29. Cant. 4. 7. Let my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved come into his garden, and eat of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169878:33"/>
fruit,</hi> Chap. 7. 13. <hi>At our gates are all manner of pleaſant fruits, new and old, which I have laid up for thee, O my Beloved.</hi> And chapt. 1. 14. <hi>Thy love is unto us a cluster of camphire.</hi> All this is the love of God through Chriſt to the Saints, and the reflections of that love, carrying up the ſouls of Saints unto God. So this tree of life is the ſame, even the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, or the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. It is compared to an oak and a teyl tree, and the holy ſeed is the ſubſtance thereof, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. 13.</p>
            <p>2. This tree of life muſt needs be the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, becauſe it bears twelve man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of fruits; which fruits are twelve de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, or ſeverall gifts of the Spirit, which are the twelve precious ſtones, or pearls that the City is founded upon.</p>
            <p>3. This tree of life muſt needs be the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; becauſe the leaves of it are to heal the Nations: Nothing can heal the Nations but Chriſt; but the leaves of this tree are to heal the Nations; and therefore they are the fruits effected and brought forth by the Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>4. There is nothing life it ſelf, or can give life for ever, but Chriſt: But this tree is life it ſelf, and will give life to them that eat it: Therefore this tree is the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169878:34"/>So then, this being clear, that this tree of life is no materiall or naturall tree, but the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and ſuch a food as will give eternall life, it muſt by the ſame grounds neceſſarily follow, that this <note n="*" place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of the two trees pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved pag. 2. is more fully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the ſeven effects brought forth by the tree, and mans righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</note> tree of knowledge of good and evill in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with it, is the righteouſneſſe of man, and is no materiall or naturall tree, no more then the other.</p>
            <p>5. The fifth degree of <hi>Adam</hi>'s riſing, was<note place="margin">5 Degree of <hi>Adams</hi> riſing.</note> to put thoſe ambitious thoughts and deſires into execution, <hi>Gen. 3. 6. Shee took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band with her, and he did eat: And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked: and they ſewed fig-leaves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made them aprons.</hi> The fifth degree of the ſubſtantiall <hi>Adam,</hi> or all thoſe that are come up to that degree, may examine themſelves by the ſhadow, which was our firſt parents, thus as it followeth; and it wil anſwer as face anſwereth face in a glaſſe: for after they are come to the fourth degree, which is to ſee the inviſible God, through the viſible things that are made; and alſo to ſee and beleeve our own righteouſneſſe, which is by the Law, to be the onely way and means by which they may become wiſe,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169878:34"/>
or like that God, or to attain heaven; And alſo the excellency of this fruit, ſo ſet forth by the ſerpent, they then with all their ſtrength follow after their own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and take of that fruit that was ſo love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the eye, and ſo much to be deſired to make one wiſe; and eats thereof, [bear with the expreſſion] for it is a Metaphor much uſed in Scripture in ſuch like words as theſe, To feed upon husks and not bread; Labour not for the meat that periſheth: Alſo there is a more pure eating held forth in Scripture, My fleſh is meat indeed; I am that heavenly Manna; Feed my Lambs, and ſuch like expreſſions: the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaking prophetically of the righteouſneſs of God: he cals it, The holy ſeed; he ſaith, It ſhall return and ſhall be eaten as a Teil-tree, and as an Oak whoſe ſubſtance is in it ſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. 13. the ſame is ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the tree of life: And as this is not to be underſtood of a naturall eating, but of a pure, inward and ſpirituall feeding of the new inward and ſpirituall man: ſo, in the like manner, that eating, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. is not to be underſtood of a naturall eating, but an inward corrupt and ſpirituall feeding of the Old man, which is to be crucified, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed and deſtroyed with that, which is husks and not bread.] I ſay, after their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169878:35"/>
approving, deſiring, and preſſing after the righteouſneſs of the Law, which is called our righteouſneſs, they then take and eat thereof; and no ſooner they have fed on that fruit, but their eyes are opened; and they know that they are naked, that is, when the creature is convinced, that his own righteouſneſs is the only meanes to bring him to heaven, or to be like God, for that is the thing the creature aims at in all his working, and the more he followeth after and feedeth on this, the more he is drawn into bondage, and ſeeth his unſufficiency in accompliſhing that end: ſo that now the naturall eyes of the underſtanding are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and they ſee that they are naked; they are not made naked by following after the righteouſneſs of the Law, but that which they thought to attain to, by it, they ſee they are not able to attain, but contrarily it doth diſcover their nakedneſs, which is their ſinne; therefore the Apoſtle ſaith by the Law is the knowledg of ſinne; the Law doth not make the creature ſinfull and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but the Law doth open eyes to ſee that which was before; for all things that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God, is ſinne, though it never tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed any outward Commandement, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in its ſelf, nor any other, (the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are unclean in his ſight) but it is not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169878:35"/>
ſinn, according to ſimilitude of <hi>Adam's</hi> tranſgreſſion, that is to ſay, nakedneſs or ſinn diſcovered; therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom. 5. 14. Nevertheleſſe, death reigned from Adam to Moſes, even over them which had not ſinned after the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Adams tranſgreſſion;</hi> that is, they had not their ſin and nakedneſs diſcovered, as it is, verſ. 13. the Apoſtle ſaith, Sinn was in the world untill the Law, but ſinn is not imputed where there is no law, that is, ſinn is not brought home to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and made ours untill the powerfull comming of the Law, which brings ſinn and nakedneſs to light; thus it was with <hi>Adam</hi> the figure, he had ſin before, but not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered untill he eat: thus it was with typical Iſrael, they had ſinn from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet not diſcovered outwardly untill <hi>Moſes</hi> gave them the Law; and thus it is with us the ſubſtance of thoſe two figures: we have ſin, and death reigning by ſinn, yet not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered untill the powerfull coming of the Law: for, the ſame effect that the fruit wrought on <hi>Adam,</hi> the ſame it doth upon the Gentiles, which never had the Law in the Letter; for when the Gentiles, which have not the Law, that is, have not the Law in the Letter, doe the things contained in the Law, which ſhew the works of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169878:36"/>
Law written in their heart, their conſcience alſo bearing witneſs, and their thoughts in the mean while, accuſing or excuſing one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15. for as <hi>Adam</hi> was alive before he eat, and was to dye upon his eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo you ſee the Gentiles dyed that death upon the powerfull coming of the Law, though they never had the law in the letter, yet they had ſin imputed inwardly, as it was typed out by an outward imputation at Mount Sinai after <hi>Moſes</hi> gave the law; thus it was with <hi>Paul</hi> alſo before he had eat or concocted the ſame fruit, he was alive, as he ſaith; <hi>I was alive once without the Law, but when the Law came, ſin revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and I dyed:</hi> as the fruit or Law did not bring ſin to <hi>Paul,</hi> but gave eyes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſin and nakedneſs; ſo in like manner, it brought not ſin to <hi>Adam,</hi> but opened his eyes, and gave ſight to diſcover and bring ſin and nakedneſs to light, which was in them before; and as <hi>Pauls</hi> life before the law came, was only but in his own appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion; ſo alſo was <hi>Adams,</hi> and their death after their eating, but only a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of what was in them; for before the law came, they believed and conceived life and power to be in themſelves to bring them to God: but when the law was come
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169878:36"/>
and they had eat of that fruit, it openeth their eyes, and diſcovereth that to be death, which they thought was life.</p>
            <p>So then, the very act of eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, or the powerful coming of the law into the ſoul, which is all one, is not ſin it ſelf, but the diſcovery of ſin, therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? is the Law ſinn? God forbid! I had not known ſinn but by the Law, Rom.</hi> 7. 7. And he ſaith, <hi>Without the Law ſin was dead;</hi> ſo I ſay, this fruit which <hi>Adam</hi> eat, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Law which brought ſinn and nakedneſs to light, it revived ſin, which before ſeemed to be dead. Therefore it is called the tree of knowledg of good and evill; ſo you ſee, whatſoever was brought upon <hi>Adam</hi> by his eating of that fruit, the ſame is brought upon them that ſeeds upon the Law of their own righteouſneſs: As for example in theſe particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, it deprives <hi>Adam</hi> of life, for he had<note place="margin">The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the fruit to him and us, alike compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in 7. particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note> life, or elſe he could not dye.</p>
            <p>The ſame doth the Law: for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>I was alive once without the Law, Rom.</hi> 7. 9.</p>
            <p>As the firſt, which was the ſhadow, had life before he eat of the fruit; ſo, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, which is the ſubſtance had life before the law came.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169878:37"/>It gives <hi>Adam</hi> the knowledg of ſin and<note place="margin">2. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the fruit.</note> nakedneſs; and the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew they were naked; (which nakednes is a metaphor which holds forth inability and ſinfulneſs in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to God.) The ſame doth the Law, I had not known ſin but by the law, <hi>Rom. 7. 7. Chap.</hi> 3. 20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the eating of the fruit brings<note place="margin">3. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the fruit.</note> fear and terrour upon <hi>Adam</hi> becauſe of ſin, Gen. 3. 9. <hi>I heard thy voice in the Garden, and I was afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame thing doth the law work on thoſe that feed on it, or to whom it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; the Apoſtle ſaith, that Chriſt took fleſh and blood upon him to deliver them who through the fear of death were all their life time ſubject to bondage, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. 15. this fear and bondage is through the law; as it will appear, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. 21. where it is ſaid, So terrible was the ſight that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſaw, that he ſaid, <hi>I exceedingly fear and quake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adams</hi> eating of this fruit, or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the law into the ſoul, anſwereth the giving of the law on <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> our ſeeding on the Law, is our coming to the Mount that burneth with fire to blackneſs and darkneſs, and the voice of words; whatſoever was effected by <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Adams</hi> eating of that fruit was the firſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</note> 
               <hi>Adams</hi> eating
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169878:37"/>
of the forbidden fruit, the ſame was in the ſecond figure at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> and is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the ſubſtance, which is every ſoul to whom the Law powerfully cometh; for as<note place="margin">The gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Law at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> was the ſecond figure.</note> at the coming of the Law at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> there was a Tempeſt, and the voice of words, which was a terrour to thoſe to whom it came; the ſame fear and terrour was effected by <hi>Adams</hi> eating that fruit, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 8. it is ſaid, <hi>They heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the Garden;</hi> this is the voice or word that they at<note place="margin">The coming of the Law into the Soul, is the ſubſtance of thoſe two Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</note> 
               <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> intreated ſhould be ſpoke to them no more; the ſame cauſed <hi>Adam</hi> to run away from God, and to be afraid and hide himſelf; <hi>Adam</hi> could not endure this voice, no more then they to whom this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation came at <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> and the reaſon of it is this, (both to <hi>Adam</hi> and all thoſe whom I compare with him, which are the Iſraelites, or all thoſe to whom the law did come) I ſay the reaſon is this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this voice is in the cool of the day; in the Hebrew word it is the [<hi>winds</hi>] of the day: ſo this voice of the <hi>Lord</hi> God was walking in the Garden, which is, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delights that man lived in; in the winds of the day; which winds and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt is all one; What is more terrible then winds or tempeſt? It was terrible to <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:169878:38"/>
and alſo to them at <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> it is called <hi>Blackneſſe and darkneſſe, and the voice of words, Hebr.</hi> 12. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>Which voice they intreated they might hear no more: It is called, <hi>The winds of the day, Gen.</hi> 3. 8. which emplyeth both black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, darkneſs and tempeſt; ſo as this voice of God was in the winds and tempeſts of the day unto <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo alſo this voice of words to thoſe at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> was in the winds of the day, even in blackneſs, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and tempeſt; whatſoever was a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper to the firſt, was alſo to the ſecond; and is the ſame to the ſubſtance, even to us that are under the diſpenſation of this day.</p>
            <p>The eating of the forbidden fruit bringeth<note place="margin">4. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the fruit. Thornes thiſtles, hay, and ſtraw, &amp;c. are taken for the fruits of our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>Jer. 4. 3. Hoſ.</hi> 10. 12.</note> a curſe upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and his whole earth; <hi>Curſed be the ground for thy ſake, in ſorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all dayes of thy life; Thornes alſo ſhall it bring forth unto thee.</hi> The law alſo in the like manner bringeth a curſe on them to whom it comes power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully into, for as many as are of the works of the law, are under the Curſe, <hi>Gal. 3. 10. The Law is not of faith, but the man that doth them, ſhall live in them, Verſe</hi> 12. ſo it was ſaid to <hi>Adam, In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat thy bread;</hi> as the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 14. is a ſpiritual living
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169878:38"/>
in the Law, ſo the meaning of that eating in<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev. 21. 1 Cor. 4. 15, 16.</hi> The world is taken for ſelf wiſdom righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or the like, this ſhall be burnt up, but the earth ſhall endure for ever, Dan. 7. 26, 27. Cha. 2. 44 Rev. 19. 6 7. Chap. 11. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 19. is of eating ſpirituall bread, a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the inward man in a laborious way under the yoak of bondage; and this his eating the fruit produceth and bringeth forth thornes and thiſtles, which ſhall be ſuch prickles in the fleſh that it ſhall choake the good ſeed that is ſowen in that ground but this earth or ground ſhall become new, and all thoſe thorns, thiſtles, hay, ſtraw or ſtubble ſhall be burnt up, and he that enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſhall enjoy it without labour, they ſhall ſet downe under their own Vine and under their own fig-trees, they ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their reſt, they ſhall run and not be faint, they ſhall mount up like Eagles and renew their ſtrength, yet the lumpe or fabrick of this earth ſhall endure for ever.</p>
            <p>And all things therein, both man and beaſt,<note place="margin">Old things ſhall be done away and all things ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith to thoſe in Chriſt, 1 Cor. 5. 27. yet they lived on this Earth. Chriſt Diſciples are taken out of the world, and yet live in the world.</note> The meaning is they ſhall be under a new diſpenſation, new law, or covenant, a new heaven and earth, a new Jeruſalem and Paradiſe and Tree of Life, new Name, new Bread, new manna for which they ſhall not labour and get with the ſweat of their faces under the ſecond diſpenſation as they do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Firſt; And as <hi>Adam</hi> did obtaine it by his eating the forbidden fruit who was
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169878:39"/>
the Type of all thoſe under the Law, who alſo get their ſpirituall bread through much labour and ſweat of their face, and yet it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieth not, and thus the latter anſwereth the former in this example.</p>
            <p>The eating of the for bidden fruit, brings death it ſelf upon <hi>Adam;</hi> For, <hi>that day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in the fifth place, to whomſoever the Law comes, it bringeth death, as it is 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fifthly. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the fruit.</note> 3. 9. We are able Miniſters of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not of the Letter, but of the Spirit, for the Letter killeth; Again it is ſaid, <hi>I was alive without the Law, but when the Law came, ſin revived, and I dyed;</hi> ſo you ſee as death was brought upon <hi>Adam,</hi> upon his eating the fruit, the ſame alſo is brought upon every one to whom the Law powerfully cometh; and the former is but only a type or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the latter; So we are not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that any fell in that fleſh of his, as is carnally and vainely underſtood, or that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dyed in him according to the generall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of men; the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks prophetically of the deſtruction of ſuch a principle or tenet as this is; ſaith he, <hi>What mean you that you uſe this Proverbe concerning the land of</hi> Iſrael; ſaying, <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have eaten ſowre grapes, and the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens teeth are ſet on edge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:169878:39"/>
               <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord, you ſhall not have any more occaſion to uſe this</hi> Proverbe <hi>in</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; <hi>The ſoul that ſinneth it ſhall dye,</hi> Ezek. 18. 2, 3, 4. And the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaks more plaine of this, and the time when it ſhall be, it is when he maketh a new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and putteth his law in their inward parts: it is when they ſhall no more every man teach his neighbour, and every man his brother; ſaying, <hi>Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt to the greateſt,</hi> Jeremiah 31. 31. to the end of the Chap. at the twenty nine verſe of the ſame Chapter he ſpeaks on this wiſe; <hi>In thoſe dayes they ſhall ſay no more, the fathers have eaten a ſowre grape, and the Childrens teeth are ſet on edg, but every one ſhall dye for his owne iniquity, every man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ateth a ſowre grape his teeth ſhall be ſet on edge;</hi> If man dyed for his own iniquity in thoſe dayes, then he died not in his fathers before; but in thoſe dayes every one did dye for his own iniquities, and therefore they did not dye nor fall in another before; we who are <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are not to look through ſhadows or through a vail; for if we are turned to the Lord, the vail is taken away; we ſee with open face, we are not ſpoken to in parables, <hi>to us it is given to know the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Kingdom,</hi> therefore let us leave off this Proverbe, in ſaying, that we were
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169878:40"/>
loſt in <hi>Adam;</hi> Let God be true, and every man a lyer; when he ſaith in thoſe dayes this Proverbe ſhall be uſed no more.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Objection</hi> from <hi>Rom. 5. 19. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 22. Where it is ſaid, <hi>All dyed in</hi> Adam; This <hi>Objection</hi> muſt admit of this anſwer as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.<note place="margin">How all are ſaid to dye in <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>1. The Apoſtle ſpeaks not his own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but condeſcends to them and ſpeaks according to this or that ſaying that they had in <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning the Fathers <hi>eating of ſowre grapes, and the childrens teeth are ſet an edg;</hi> he ſpeaks to them here in this as unto thoſe <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. where he ſaith, <hi>the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving husband is ſanctified by the believing wife, and the unbelieving Wife is ſanctified by the believing Husband<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> or elſe <hi>were the children uncleane, but now they are holy.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle here ſpeaks not his own opinion (for he had caſt of all this holineſſe of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and what priviledg ſoever he had by it, and accounts it loſſe and as droſſe and dung) but he ſpeaks according to their belief or tenet in the time of the Law, which was, if a Circumciſed perſon was joyned to an uncircumciſed, yet their ſeed ſhould be accounted to be within the Covenant or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and not unclean; and from this their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he goes to take advantage and reconcile them together, by what they themſelves
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169878:40"/>
held, and ſo in this place he doth endeavour to illuſtrate &amp; make out life to all in Chriſt, by that which they held concerning <hi>Adam,</hi> that is that their teeth was ſet an edge by his eating ſowre grapes; he doth in this place as he doth in the <hi>Hebraws</hi> where he holds out the excellency of the myſtery of Chriſt by the Miniſtery that they were beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secon.</hi> We die in <hi>Adam,</hi> tis trve, all have held it to be a truth, but they have not lookt to the end of things, becauſe their mindes are blinded, and the vaile is over their hearts and ſhall be till they are turned to the Lord, and then this Proverbe ſhall be uſed no more.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How may we be ſaid to die in</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We may be ſaid to die in him in an allegoricall ſence; that is, he by his death did ſhadow out all thoſe that came to that State or degree as he was in; marke what the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, Tell me you little children, do you not hear the Law read? ſo he goes to tell them of the Law thus, It is written, <hi>Abraham</hi> had two Sonnes, the one by a bond-Maid, the other by a free-Woman; this he tels them that in the myſtery or the allegoricall ſence is the Law, as he ſaith afterwards; for this <hi>Hagar</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:169878:41"/>
is mount <hi>Sinai</hi> in <hi>Arabia</hi> &amp; anſwereth to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> which now is &amp; is in bondage with<note place="margin">Galla. 4. 25.</note> her children; this <hi>Hagar</hi> is mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> ſaith he; this is as plain a ſpeech as to ſay all dyed in <hi>Adam,</hi> but yet he looks through this <hi>Hagar</hi> and Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> to the Jews in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage under the Law which he cals <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> So in like manner he looks through our firſt Parents when he ſaith all dyed in <hi>Adam,</hi> and meanes them who were come to that eſtate and degree; So then he by his death did figure out all that came to that degree, that they ſhould come to it that way, as he did; to die in <hi>Adam,</hi> is to crucifie the old man and dye to ones own righteouſneſſe and ſtrength daily; ſo then his death did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this death of ours, as he by his death did aſſure us that we ſhall follow him; in this ſence we may be ſaid to die in him, ſuch Scriptures, which ſay that we all died in <hi>Adam,</hi> muſt be further anſwered thus by the like Scriptures, and underſtood accordingly as theſe are.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is ſaid to be ſlain from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world; And, I am that heavenly Manna that came down from heaven; And <hi>Babylon</hi> is fallen, is fallen: when it is ſaid<note place="margin">Rev. 13. 8. &amp; 18. 2, 4.</note> afterwards, Come out of her my people; all this while this is but in Gods account, or in the ſhadow or repreſentation; ſo the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169878:41"/>
eat Manna, &amp; drank of that rock that followed them, and that rock was Chriſt, but not ſubſtantially but parabolically; or elſe it is to be underſtood as ſure as it is in part, ſo it ſhall be in our account, ſo it ſhal be in the ſubſtance, ſo it ſhall be wholly; thus we muſt underſtand our death in <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, we are all dead men in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are all dead in the ſhadow.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we are all dead in that nature and earneſt; the whole world is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and whole payment, which muſt be brought into the ſame place as the earneſt was; we muſt come the ſame way as he did, and bear our burthens; and by his death he doth aſſure us that we ſhall dye aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it were already done in him.</p>
            <p>Again, when we dyed, we dyed in <hi>Adam;</hi> for every carnall man is <hi>Adam;</hi> yet all the carnality that ever was, is, or ſhall be, is <hi>Adam</hi> the old man as it is formerly proved: And in this <hi>Adam,</hi> all thoſe to whom the law cometh, muſt dye, and are dead already in Gods account, or in the ſhadow and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, as hath been proved. Thus much in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Objection.</p>
            <p>Object. Adams <hi>eating the forbidden fruit did cauſe him to cloath himſelf
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169878:42"/>
with fig-leafes; which leafes are the leafes of the ſame tree; as the eating of the fruit did open their eyes to ſee their nakedneſs; and upon the ſight thereof they were put upon action to cover this nakedueſſe with the leafs of the Tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſame thing doth the law effect on<note place="margin">6. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the friut.</note> them to whom it comes; for when the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the law comes in upon the ſoul or heart, and diſcovereth nakedneſs or ſin, then theſe impreſſions put the creature upon ſome thing that it conceives to be a duty to hide this ſinne, or to be, as it were, a Mediator to appeaſe the wrath of God, and thereby to quiet and ſatisfie its own conſcience; ſo theſe our good works are the figg-leafs, for figg-leafs are very broad, and ſo are our good works: although carnal perſons apprehend themſelves to be very naked and ſinfull; yet if they can but faſt and do pennance, and ſay thus many pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, then preſently ſinn, which is their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, is covered, and their conſcience is quieted: ſo then, theſe good works are the leafs of the tree of knowledge of good and evil; under which figg-tree all men are found ſitting to whom the ſecond diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation comes; it findes us there and knows us before we know it, as you may ſee, <hi>John</hi> 1. 48. where Chriſt ſpake in anſwer to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaneel's</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:169878:42"/>
queſtion, whether he knew him Chriſt ſaith unto him, <hi>That he knew him before Philip called him under the fig-tree;</hi> the leafs of the tree of life ſhall be for the healing of the Nations: What are the leafs of the tree of life? only the effects of the fruit, which fruit is the Spirit of God; and the effects are our good works, brought forth by that Spirit, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your Father which is in heaven, Matthew 5. 16. 1 Peter 2. 12. Revelat.</hi> 11. 13. Thus be theſe leafs of the tree of life effected and brought forth by the Spirit; the Nations ſhall be wonn, recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and healed, and ſhall glorifie God; by this you may the more clearly ſee what are the leafs of the firſt tree, they are our good works ſpringing forth from the law; it ſhal heal and cover them too in their own appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions; but when the ſecond fruit is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to eat, they ſhal come from under that figg-tree, they ſhall caſt their garments away as filthy rags and menſtruous clouts, as <hi>Paul</hi> did.</p>
            <p>For when this ſecond diſpenſation comes, which is the fruit of the tree of life, or Chriſt in the ſoul, it findes no fruit but only leafs, on which he pronounceth a curſe, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169878:43"/>
it withereth away, and is no more ſeen for ever in that ſoul, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 19. Thus alſo you may ſee, that as <hi>Adam</hi>'s eating the fruit, cauſed him to cloath himſelf with fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leafs; the ſame doth the powerfull coming of the law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adams</hi> eating of the forbidden fruit, did<note place="margin">7. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the fruit.</note> cauſe him to hide himſelf amongſt the trees of the garden, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 8; the ſame thing doth the Law effect in them, to whom it cometh; when God cometh in that deſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with voyces in the wind or tempeſt of that day, and maketh the creature afraid, the creature preſently runs away and hides it ſelf in the trees of the garden, which trees are theſe two things; the firſt ſort and greateſt ſhelter that the creature hides it ſelfe under from the wrath of God, is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and tenents of the fathers or them that pretend to be Miniſters of the people, unto which the creature being frighted runs to tell their eſtate, to the end they may have their conſciences quieted; and after confeſſion, by thoſe that are in bondage under the law, to theſe trees of <hi>Lebanon.</hi> And alſo there being admoniſhed by theſe tall Cedars in their humane traditions, they then give them abſolution and remiſſion of their ſinnes, that is to ſay, their words take
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169878:43"/>
effect upon the heart of the fearfull, and their ſinnes are remited declaratively; thus they truſt to what others ſay, and pinn themſelves to them, when they are not made one in the thing that they profeſs; and thus their conſcience is quieted, they having hid themſelves from God in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſpenſation among the trees, which are ſome pleaſant Tenents or doctrines of ſalvation, duties and formes from humane traditions: theſe are the trees which men hide themſelves from God in. The gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of figg-leafs in the ſixth Compariſon, was a work of the law only; but their hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves among the trees of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, is from humane tradition and groſſe Idolatry: For proof hereof, ſee <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 18. where the Prophet ſpeaks in reference to thoſe trees, which are the Prieſts, thus, <hi>They eat up the ſinne of my people:</hi> and verſe 12, 13. the Prophet ſpeakes in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the people; thus, <hi>My people ask counſell after ſtocks, and their ſtaffs declare unto them; for the ſpirit of whoredome hath cauſed them to erre:</hi> Thoſe ſtocks and ſtaffs are the Prieſts; at the 13 verſe, he ſpeakes thus, <hi>They ſacrifice upon the tops of moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and burn incenſe upon the hils, under Oaks and Poplar trees, and Elmes, becauſe the ſhadow thereof is good:</hi> Theſe ſhadows
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169878:44"/>
cover them from theſe winds and tempeſt, which is the voice of God in the law; and as <hi>Adam</hi> in his greateſt fear, fled and hid himſelf, and had his ſinne, as it were, eaten up or covered by the ſhadows of theſe trees, ſo the ſinne of theſe Iſraelites, was, as it were, eaten up: This was held forth by <hi>Iſhmael</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hagar,</hi> or the ſonne of the Covenant of works; he was caſt under a ſhrub in his greateſt agony, when all his refreſhment of water was gone; In this he held forth the ſonnes of the Covenant of works, who alſo doe fly from the voice of God, in the wind of the day, and hide themſelves under the ſhadow of theſe trees, becauſe it brings peace, and ſeemeth to be good.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>You will ſay,</hi> Adam <hi>had no ſuch trees as Prieſts or Teachers to hide himſelf under.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant that, if you ſpeak of theſe perſons; but he ſought out thoſe opinions, traditions and inventions, as they have ſince learned, and others have them now without ſo much labour; and thus under thoſe trees they ſhelter themſelves from the wrath of God; The ſecond ſort of trees are ſome particular pleaſure or delights; I told you the Garden it ſelf was all manner of pleaſures or delights in generall, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169878:44"/>
we have eaten of the Tree of knowledge of good and evill, and our eyes are opened thereby we are driven as it were out of this carnall pleaſure and delight in generall; ſo that we lye under a heavy yoak of bondage in a mournfull and heavy condition, ſo that the ſoul is as it were brought downe to hell; then many times ſuch a Soul ſpies out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of ſhelter which may be underſtood to be company, playing, muſick, ſinging, or any ſuch kind of recreation; for ſaith ſuch a one, when I am out of Company I am ſo melancholy and diſcontented and oppreſſed in my conſcience that I know not what to do, and from hence they ſeek after recreation to put away melancholy humors, and cover their ſinnes under ſuch trees as theſe; here you may ſee whatſoever was produced and effected in <hi>Adam</hi> by eating the forbidden fruit in theſe ſeven particulars; the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is produced and effected by the law on whom it powerfully commeth; whoſoever feedeth on it, it bringeth him into the ſame condition as the fruit brought <hi>Adam</hi> into; and this may be a ſufficient ground or reaſon to prove that the tree of knowledge of good and evill and the Law to be one and the ſame.</p>
            <p>The ſixt degree of <hi>Adams</hi> riſing is thus as it followeth; unto <hi>Adam</hi> alſo &amp; to his Wife did
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169878:45"/>
the Lord God make Coats of skins; As in the five former degrees of <hi>Adams</hi> riſing, I have endeavoured to ſhew the ſubſtance or end of things; ſo I ſhall in this ſixth degree.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What this cloathing is in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and Secondly, compare us with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> in ſhewing how and when we are cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with this cloathing. Firſt, this cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with skins in the ſubſtance, is the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, of Faith and Love, this was the cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that <hi>Iohn</hi> was cloathed in: for the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt ſaith, <hi>His cloathing was of Camels haire, and a Girdle of a skin;</hi> this righteouſneſſe of God by ſaith is figured out by a skin, in as much as it is a ſhield to cover the creature and keep it warme, and ſecure the life and inwards of a creature and alſo bind up the fleſh, bones and ſinews, and is the very ſtrength thereof, the ſame is the righteouſnes of faith, and love to the inward man; therefore Chriſt is ſaid to bind up the broken and cloath the naked; the Apoſtle cals it the Armour of God; therefore ſaith he, having your loynes girt about with truth, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on the breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſſe <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 13, 14. The ſame Apoſtle cals it the breaſt-plate of Faith and Love, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 58. but <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking plainer to this thing, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 13. ſaith he; <hi>Therefore gird up the loynes of your minds, and be ſober and hope to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169878:45"/>
the end;</hi> ſo this cloathing is the righteouſnes of faith, love and truth which girds and binds up the loynes of the inward man in faith and love unto God; this being true that this cloathing in the ſubſtance is the righteouſneſſe of faith and love: we ſhall in the next place take notice, when and how this clothing is put on. God ſuffers man to run on in the firſt diſpenſation, working and getting his bread with the ſweat of his face, and clothing himſelf with fig-leaves to cover his nakedneſſe; and in this his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God takes advantage, and as it were meets man halfe way, and uncloathes him of that cloathing of leaves, and cloaths him with another cloathing; This was figured out in that of <hi>Adam,</hi> and alſo in that of Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> with that of <hi>Iohn;</hi> for <hi>Iohn</hi> differed from the diſpenſation of Mount <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai</hi> both in his meat and cloathing, which are both to be underſtood, in a ſpirituall ſence; his meat was Locuſt and wild Hony, that is he fed on Chriſt through dark ſhadows, he fed on him as he was in the fleſh; as<note place="margin">John 14. 23. Luke 24. 25, 26.</note> Chriſts Diſciples did, and were reproved by him for it, or as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though afterwards he ſaw his error, when he ſaith, although I have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth deſire I to know him ſo no more, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:169878:46"/>And thus <hi>Iohn</hi> fed upon Chriſt through ſhadows, and in this reſpect his meat is ſaid to bee Wilde Honey; for the pure Word of God which is Chriſt, is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Hony and Hony Combe, but <hi>Iohn</hi> fed not on this hony alone, but upon Locuſts which is the traditions and inventions, and errours of men, which devoure and eat like a Canker; as you may ſee <hi>Exod. 11. 12. Rev.</hi> 9. 3, 7. Thus <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw ſomething darkly of Chriſt, and ſomething of error. <hi>Iohn</hi> muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, Chriſt muſt encr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 30. therfore <hi>Iohns</hi> Diſciples and Chriſt could not agree, much leſſe <hi>Moſes</hi> Diſciples and Chriſts, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the comming of the Comforter. <hi>Iohn</hi> is the greateſt of all the Prophets, but the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven is greater then <hi>Iohn;</hi> yet this diſpenſation of <hi>Iohn</hi> was of God in oppoſition to that of Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> which may be ſaid to be of man; It was the ſecond diſpenſation, and anſwers that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Adams</hi> cloathing with skins, which was of God in oppoſition to <hi>Adams</hi> firſt cloathing, which was of himſelf; it is alſo a figure of that righteouſneſſe of faith and love, and as I told you before, according to the figure: God ſuffers men to run on in the firſt diſpenſation after the powerfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Law to the creature, and gives him the knowledg of ſinne which is his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169878:46"/>
then the creature runs on furiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly, and endeavours to cover himſelf with a Garment of his own making, and in this his toyling under a heavy yoak of bondage and labouring therein, to become like God, then God as it were condeſcends and meets him, and uncloaths him of that menſtruous cloathing which could not well keep him warme, and cloaths him with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Faith, and binds up the loynes of his mind unto God with this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Girdle; and as in the ſhadow there was two cloathings to bring them up to God; the firſt is of mans owne which bringeth him on his way; the ſecond of Gods, which brings him to the end of his Journy; man muſt be cloathed with theſe two cloathings before he come to God, and that you may ſee as followeth; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>For what the Law could not do in that it was weake through the fleſh, God ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Sonne in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſin condemned ſin in the fleſh;</hi> here you may ſee theſe two diſpenſations or cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; Firſt, the Law, or figleaves; and this did endeavour, but it could not doe that which it was put upon to doe; but the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>God ſent his own Sonne in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh,</hi> and this is Gods own diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or ſecond cloathing which condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169878:47"/>
ſin in the fleſh: this in the cloathing of God which hides and covers ſin: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſins are covered:</hi> this is repeated <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 7. The firſt cloathing could not cover our ſins nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from God, nor from us. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in reference to this cloathing, thus: but we are all as unclean things, and all out righteouſneſſe is as filthy rags, and we all do fade as a leaf, and our iniquities like the winde, have taken us away, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64. 6. This firſt cloathing is the ſame that <hi>Joſhua</hi> was cloathed with, which the Angel was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to take away from him that filthy garment; and alſo he was cloathed with change of rayment, which was the ſecond diſpenſation, which is the righteouſneſs of faith and love, which is called fine linnen, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. 11.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle had experience of theſe two cloathings, and he being uncloathed by God of the firſt cloathing, which he did ſo much approve of, he now abhors it, and counted it as droſſe and dung, in reſpect of the ſecond, as you may ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 7, 8, 9. in theſe words: <hi>But what things were gain to me, thoſe I counted loſſe for Chriſt; yea, doubteſſe I account all things but loſſe for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſſe of all
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169878:47"/>
things, and I account them but dung, that I may win Chriſt, and be found in him, not having mine own righteouſneſſe which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith.</hi> Thus you ſee how we are cloathed with the fig-leaves of our own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and how the ſhadow anſwers the ſubſtance in theſe ſix Degrees, in ſhewing how far men go in their own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in cloathing themſelves with fig-leaves before they are clothed by God with his righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Some may ſay, The firſt diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation was of God, for God gave it at Mount Sinai.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, all things, the crooked Serpent, and whatſoever is called evill, is of God in one ſenſe; but it is not of God in another ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As a ſmall plant, or any other thing in their firſt appearance from nothing, may be ſaid to be made by God, in this ſenſe all things are of God.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, In their growth they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards do naturally bring forth fruit; that fruit thus brought forth cannot be ſaid to be made by God under the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration as the plant was firſt made; but as theſe plants have ſtrength and power in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169878:48"/>
their natures to bring forth fruit in time, in this ſenſe, in making the tree, the fruit may be ſaid to be made of God: So God made man uncapable, having neither fruit of ſin or righteouſneſſe, but with ſtrength<note place="margin">Thus man was made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, &amp; no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</note> in their nature through growth to bring forth fruit: In this ſenſe all things may be ſaid to be made by God, as he is the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, and makes things with ſtrength in their nature to bring forth fruit through growth; in this ſenſe that diſpenſation was of God as he was the originall of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but not as he was the actor of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: For power is left in all vegetative and ſenſitive creatures to bring forth fruit.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Objection ſaith, this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation was Gods, becauſe it was given at Mount Sinai.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, By the giving of the Law at Mount Sinai, God did figure out or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent that which was placed in man na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally by creation; and what blackneſſe, darkneſs, and tempeſt would naturally grow up in man: So then, that diſpenſation was not of God; but God did repreſent and figure out by it what man ſhould naturally be brought unto. And this you may ſee in reading of theſe Scriptures here quoted, that the diſpenſation given at Mount Sinai was not of God according to his nature,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169878:48"/>
               <hi>Hebr. 7. 16, 18, 19. Chapt.</hi> 8. 2, 5. and 9. 8. <hi>Gal. 4. 9. Act. 7. 48, 49, 50. God is light, and in him is no darkneſſe at all:</hi> but that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of Mount Sinai was blackneſs, darkneſs and tempeſt, therefore it was not of God; wrath is not in God: but in this diſpenſation was nothing but wrath, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not of God; for God comes in a ſtill voice, therefore not in blackneſſe and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt. It is not of God in reſpect of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall influence, but it is of God as he is the Originall or Creator of all things, who gave that Law at Mount Sinai, to ſignifie what was in man naturally before, and to ſtir up that nature in man, that ſin might appear exceeding ſinfull, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 13. and 5. 20.</p>
            <p>And as the firſt is not of God, but natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in man; ſo the ſecond diſpenſation is not of man, that is, it is not naturall to man to live in it, no more then it is for the earth to aſcend up into the heaven out of its own element: this is the gift of God through the influence of the Spirit: this is grace in oppoſition to any thing in man, which is called works; this is Gods righteouſneſſe or cloathing, in oppoſition to mans righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe or cloathing of fig-leaves. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore miſtake not, you that run headlong, and look at things in generall, who ſay, all
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169878:49"/>
men are alike, for all things are of God, and all do the works of God. I have granted this under this conſideration, as he is the Originall; but look who is of God under a ſecond diſpenſation: look not onely who is naturally made by God, and ſo is of God, but look who is ſpiritually made, and one with God in the nature of God: And then if you are one with them, your love will more principally extend to them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond diſpenſation, or cloathing of the righteouſneſs of God, doth that which was endeavoured to be done by the firſt, even the Law, or mans righteouſneſſe; that is to ſay, to convince man of ſin; which is their caſting out of Paradiſe or pleaſure, which all men naturally live in: But this firſt diſpenſation of the Law could not convince men of all ſin, for it could not convince them that their own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe was ſin, and ſo the Law was weak through the fleſh: and therefore God cometh forth in the likeneſſe of fleſh.</p>
            <p>I ſhould ſnew you a myſtery touching the Trinity, which hath been hidden from the wiſe men of the world: But I ſhall onely point at it now, and further cleer it when opportunity ſerves.</p>
            <p>God caſteth man out of Paradiſe by one
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169878:49"/>
power manifeſting it ſelf, or working three ways; Firſt, conſidered as a Creater in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king man in that nature to grow up into the knowledg of a Law, which Law brought man part of his way out of Paradiſe or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and this is of God conſidered as a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, as is before ſhewed. The ſecond way God manifeſt himſelf in caſting man out of carnall pleaſure and delight, is that; ſpirit of God that moved upon the waters and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the world with all things therein, which ſpirit afterward took up fleſh and dwelt therein, even in the man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> on whom all the ends of the earth are to look to and be ſaved, and what could not be done by God conſidered as a Creator in giving the creature a law in nature to caſt out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that is done by the ſecond diſpenſation which is called his own Sonne; he is called ſo in regard he is the ſecond power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth from God, he is after the firſt as a ſonne is after a father; and what the firſt could not do in that it was weak through the fleſh, God ſent his own Sonne in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſinne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned ſin in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Here is one ſending, and that is God in his eternall Effence; Secondly, here is one ſent by the firſt, that is God in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and power, which is the Godhead
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169878:50"/>
of Chriſt: And yet the father remaineth full in himſelf, as a man after he hath a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſonne; And Thirdly, How this ſecond was ſent, that is in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh; And Fourthly, The end of his ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was to condemn ſin in the fleſh; he condemns ſin in the fleſh under theſe two conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As a figure which figureth out all thoſe on whom this anointing or ſpirit of God comes into; thus he threatneth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth ſinne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He condemns ſinne as being an Enſigne to be held to all thoſe that he is a figure of, to the end that they in the beholding of him may be changed into the ſame Image and become one with himſelf; This is the ſecond diſpenſation and that cloathing of skins which <hi>Adam</hi> was clothed with; and as it was endeavoured by the firſt diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to caſt man out of carnal pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, it was farre more endeavoured, and neerer accompliſhed by the ſecond diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for where it was ſaid, unto <hi>Adam</hi> and his wife, did the Lord God make coats of Skins, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. 21. In the next verſe it is ſaid, <hi>Behold, the man is become like one of us:</hi> Man muſt be cloathed by God with the righteouſneſs of God, before man become like God in either of his three relations; ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169878:50"/>
you ſee through the ſecond diſpenſation man became like God, and is alſo caſt out of his carnall pleaſure and delight; God is the drawer of man out of ſinne, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>There is a third diſpenſation, by which<note place="margin">The 7th. degree of Adams riſing.</note> man is wholly caſt out of paradiſe, kept out of paradiſe, and brought in to a ſecond and glorious paradiſe, and that is the Spirit or Comforter; the going away of the firſt, is the coming of the ſecond; that of <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> muſt decreaſe, Chriſt muſt increaſe; ſo the going away of the ſecond, is the coming of the third: as Moſes gave place to Chriſt, ſo Chriſt gave place to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter: <hi>It is expedient that I goe away, or elſe the Comforter cannot come:</hi> The firſt witneſſeth to the ſecond, and ſaith, <hi>Him ſhall ye hear in all things:</hi> The ſecond wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefleth to the third, and ſaith, <hi>I will ſend the Comforter, and he ſhall lead you into all truth:</hi> Upon the knowing of the third, the ſecond is to be known no more: <hi>Although I have known Chriſt after the fleſh yet henceforth deſire I to know him ſo no more:</hi> This is the new and ſpirituall birth; for he that is in Chriſt, is a new creature; to him old things are done away, and all things muſt become new; the law did convince of Sin, Chriſt in the fleſh did convince of Sin,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169878:51"/>
and ſo endevoured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to make man like God, and caſt him out of ſelviſh and carnall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe: but what the ſecond diſpenſation could not doe, the third diſpenſation is ſent to doe it; and therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>When the Comforter commeth, he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the world of ſin, righteouſneſſe, and judgment.</hi> He ſhall convince the world of ſin, the Law did endevour this, and Chriſt did endevour this, and may be ſaid to doe it as a meanes, but it is the Spirit it ſelf, that doth compleatly accompliſh this work: this is the Word of God that divideth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the joynts and marrow, and is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart; none can call Jeſus Chriſt but by this Spirit, and this is that which convinceth of ſin, and caſteth man out of carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight: and not only ſo, but by this Spirit we are brought into the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typicall and ſpirituall paradiſe of God, and therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He ſhall take of mine, and ſhew it unto you:</hi> This is made good to the Apoſtle, he being under this diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, who witneſſeth the accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment of what was written by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> touching this diſpenſation, as it is written, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, non ear hath not heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man, but God hath revealed them unto us by
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169878:51"/>
his ſpirit: For, the Spirit ſearcheth all things, even the deep things of God, 1 Cor.</hi> 2. 9, 10. Thus doth the Spirit take of God and ſhew it unto us; this is the ſword, and this is the Cherubim that keeps the way of the tree of life, that none can come to it, but thoſe whom it takes up to that para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, Such a man I knew who was taken up into Paradiſe and heard unſpeakablewords, which it is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a man to utter: this is the fire that will burn up all things, as hay, ſtubble, ſtraw, or whatſoever is not of its own planting, this ſhall be poured out upon the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of <hi>Judah,</hi> they ſhall be as a hearth of fire among wood, and as a torch in a ſheaf of corn: this is the Cherubim that brought a coal of fire from the Altar unto <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> by which he had his iniquities forgiven and was made fit to goe with Gods meſſage; when man is drove out of his carnality by this Spirit, he is fit to till the ground from whence he was taken. We may ſee God in a generall way, through the other two diſpenſations; but none can know God, Scripture, Sinne, or Righteouſneſs, but by the Spirit; all rules are uncertain but this rule of the new Creature, <hi>and as many as walk according to this rule, peace be unto them, and to the Iſrael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:169878:52"/>And thus you ſee how one God through 3 diſcoveries doth caſt man out of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſure and delight, therefore let us put him out, a ſpeech after the manner of men, which holds forth abundance of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, of which I have many things to ſay and hard to be uttered or underſtood, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are ſo dull of hearing; that which I promiſed I ſhall here commend to the wiſe, and onely point at two general Uſes, and leave what other Uſes may be made of it unto you, or the power of God leading you out unto it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If this be a truth that is here delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> that no man fell in <hi>Adam</hi> really but figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively as he did repreſent and aſſure us by his fall that we ſhould fall in the like manner; from hence we ſhould be reconciled unto God, and not to ſay that God is ſuch a hard<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 24.</note> Maſter, reaping where he never ſowes, and charge him with injuſtice, iniquity and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, in ſaying, that all ſhould dye for one mans fault; you that are Chriſtians and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the new Covenant, what meane you by this Proverbe? what meane you to ſay, the fathers eat ſower grapes and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens teeth are ſet an edg? and to ſhift your<note place="margin">Jer. 31. 29. Ezek. 12. 24.</note> owne necks out of the coller in charging your ſinne upon another; what meane you to make God a lyar? when he ſaith; As I
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169878:52"/>
live, this Proverbe ſhall be no more, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſhall dye for his own iniquity; and he that eateth the ſowre grapes, his teeth ſhall be ſet on edg; therefore if you live in thoſe dayes as the Prophets points at; if you are Iſraell according to the Spirit; if you are turned to the Lord; this vail of <hi>Adam</hi> wil be taken away aſ well as the vail of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, Tabernacle or Altar meats or drinks, waſhings or purifyings or whatſoever of that nature, they were all truths once, but when the ſubſtance came, the ſhadow was to be taken away as wel in the one as the other, therefore be you reconciled unto God; charge not God with injuſtice; let this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe be heard no more in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> let God be true, and every man a lyer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If <hi>Adam</hi> in his riſing did figure<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> out and aſſure us that we ſhould follow him through theſe ſever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll diſpenſations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen all ſorts of men ought to be reconciled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thou that art not in Paradiſe, and<note place="margin">A word to ſeven degrees of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</note> art not capable of pleaſure and delights: thou canſt not come in of thy ſelf, untill thou art put in by God; why ſhould he that is put in, hate thee who liveſt in thy own ſtation, for all were as thou art?</p>
            <p>Second. If thou art put into carnall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, and liveſt in thy pleaſure and delights
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169878:53"/>
by reaſon of growth, and haſt no reſtraint in thy nature, but mayeſt ſatisfie thy ſelf in every ſinfull pleaſure, I know thou wilt hate all that are above thee, that run not with thee into the ſame exceſſe of riot; but take heed; by the viſible things that are made thou ſhalt be left without excuſe and ſee thy nakedneſſe and be judged, condemned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If thou art come to ſee the inviſible God by the viſible things that are made, then thou wilt leave the other trees in ſome meaſure, and look into the middeſt of the Garden, upon thy own righteouſnes which will be very lovely to thy eye, and the only thing to make thee wife and become like God in thy own apprehenſion; Judge not them that are above thee, for thou haſt been once deceived already.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If thou haſt eaten of the tree that thou ſo much deſireſt to make thee wiſe, which is thy own righteouſneſs, then thy eyes are opened and thou ſeeſt thy naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and alſo what is good and evil accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods eſtimation of good and evill; but here lies thy miſery, thou are dead to do good and alive to doe evil; for thou thoughtſt thou hadſt life and power in thy ſelf to become like God by thy own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, but thou ſhalt ſee upon thy eating
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169878:53"/>
thereof, thou ſhalt becom dead, without po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; ſtrength in thy ſelf, thou ſhalt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be dead to do good, but fear &amp; death ſhal ſeaſe on thee, when thou heareſt the voyce of God in the winds of the day <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 10.<note place="margin">Eſa. 6. 5. Rom. 7. 24. Heb. 13. 19, 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, Then if thou art in this toyling condition, thou wilt cry with <hi>Adam, I was afaid;</hi> with <hi>Iſaiah, I am a man undone;</hi> with <hi>Paul, O wretched man that I am, who ſhal deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me from this body of death?</hi> with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who intreated they might hear that voyce no more it was ſo terrible to them; and ſo it will be unto thee, it wil make thee hide thy ſelf from God under ſome pleaſing opinions or tenents, and cloath thy ſelf with thy good works of faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and praying, and ſuch like duties which are the fruits of thy own righteouſneſs; this thou wilt be zealous in following after, thy own righteouſneſs, and hate all thoſe that are above thee or below thee. Be not to zealous; this is the third time thou haſt been deceived, thou wilt again be deceived, and ſee all this thy righteouſneſs to be as droſſe &amp; dung, and that which thou thinkeſt to be gain thou wilt account loſſe, <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians</hi> 3. 7. 8.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, If thou art clothed with the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of faith, or this girdle of a skin, thou haſt a glorious clothing which will
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169878:54"/>
bind up the loyns of thy mind to the head, by which all the body by joynts and bands having nouriſhment miniſtered and knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, increaſeth with the increaſe of God; and thus thou ſhalt grow from one degree to another under this ſecond di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation, as thou didſt under the firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till thou comeſt to perfection, and this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is the ſeventh degree, this is the Sabboth or reſt, we having laboured and toyled theſe ſix days, that is under theſe ſix degrees, and followed God who is our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; we muſt all ſo enter into our reſt with him, he that is entred into his reſt<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 10.</note> hath ceaſed from all his works, as God did from his: this is the year of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> this is <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam;</hi> the firſt ſix generations work and toyl every one his day, and get their ſpiritual bread with the ſweat of their face, for the ſpace of five thouſand five hundred and fourteen years, the years of their ſix dayes being added to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and they being a figure of the carnal world in labour, bondage and time, which was to indure the ſpace of five thouſand five<note place="margin">The dawning of the day at the year 5514.</note> hundred and fourteen yeers in its height, and then the end ſhall come nigh, and a new world ſhall begin, in which ſhall dwell righteouſneſs: <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> from his ſixty fifth year was a figure of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169878:54"/>
his day of reſt, in which the Kingdoms of this world ſhould become the Kingdoms of the Lord and his Chriſt, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and dominions, and the greateſt of the Kingdome under the whole Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſhall be given to the people of the Saints, and all ſhall ſerve and obey him; theſe Saints are <hi>Enoch</hi> in the ſubſtance, who ſucceedeth the ſix generations or dayes of labour; this is that <hi>Enoch</hi> that was not, for<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Enoch</hi> is not of the world, as Chriſts diſciples are not of the world, but tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en out. It is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing cleared at the year 5579.</note> God took him up unto himſelf, and he ſhall walk with God in the heavenly Jeruſalem, where there ſhall be no unclean thing, and they ſhall be his people, and God himſelf will he their God; they ſhall not only walk with God, but they ſhall dwel in God and God in them, 1 <hi>John 4. chap. verſes</hi> 12. 13. and 16. and as it is true there is a general &amp; compleat perfection or reſt for the Saints at the end of five thouſand five hundred ſeventy nine years (<hi>Enoch</hi>'s ſixty five years being added, which was the time before God took him) in this earth, although not in this carnal world, as you may ſee in theſe quotations. <hi>Rev. 15. 3, 4. Dan. 7. 14. 26. Chap. 2. 44. Luk. 1. 33. Micah 4. 7. Zeph. 3. 19. Zach.</hi> 1. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>It is alſo as true, That there is a perfection and reſt to ſome, though not ſo compleat in the ſix dayes, or ſix generations: there are
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169878:55"/>
ſome that walk with God, and reſt with God on his Sabbath in the time of theſe ſix dayes before this Sabbath is come in generall, of whom <hi>Enoch</hi> was a type; and both <hi>Enoch</hi> and they are a type and a figure of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and glorious reſt, as is before ſpoken of. Therefore, Brethren, if this be the reſult, that the ſix generations, and the ſix days did hold forth ſix degrees or diſpenſations to continue for ſo many years, as is before-mentioned; and alſo <hi>Enoch</hi> and the Sabbath in their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding theſe ſix generations or dayes, did hold forth our reſt with God, and living in perfection, then we ought in reaſon to be reconciled together. Let not him that is ſtrong, who liveth in the ſixt or ſeventh day, deſpiſe him that is weak, that lives in the firſt or darkeſt dayes or diſpenſations; <hi>Nor let not him that is weake, judge him that is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſtreng; for God hath received him, he walketh with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will think him to be a mutherer that ſhould endevour to make all mankind to eat one ſort of meat; either to make old men to eat milk or ſuck the breaſt; or elſe to make new born Babes to eat ſuch groſs meat as old men do; ſuch will be murtherers of the body: ſo in the like manner are they ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murtherers that will bring all men into one conformity; nay, they are farr worſe then
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169878:55"/>
the firſt; for theſe doe not only make ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men feed upon ſpirituall meat of any kinde, but upon Dogs meat and Husks, and ſuch as they themſelves feed on. I am not offended with them for their feeding, but in that they go to take away my liberty, theſe are ſoul. murtherers to thoſe who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to them; and alſo body-murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to them that will not conform with them: But this Antichriſt that thus exalts himſelf above all that is called god in the Saints, ſhall be deſtroyed by the brightneſs of his coming; they ought to have the liberty of their conſciences, be they never ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in Worſhip.</p>
            <p>But if thy Conſcience be to take away my liberty in worſhip, ought to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed as an evil doer, or as one endevour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make murther, this is of <hi>Cain,</hi> whoſe ſeed thou art; this is that City in which all the blood of the Saints ſhall be found in her; all that dare to publiſh ſuch a Tenet, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to doe it, have committed murther, and ought to dye by the Law of God, and Law of reaſon; as all mankinde cannot live upon one ſort of naturall meat, except ſome muſt ſtarve: neither can the ſpirituall ſeed, live all upon one ſort of ſpiritual food; therefore Chriſt ſpeaketh to the multitude in parables, but ſaith to his Diſciples, Unto
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169878:56"/>
you it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdom: Chriſt ſpeaks not according to the Excellency of his own knowledg and light, but condiſcends to their weakneſs in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to their capacity, therefore he ſaith to his Diſciples, I have many things to ſay, but you cannot bear them now.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> endevoureth to ſpeak according to the capacity of them he ſpeaks to, as you may ſee, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 4. And <hi>my ſpeech and my preaching was not with enticing words of mans wiſdom, but in the demonſtration of the ſpirit and power: Howbeit we ſpeak wiſdom among them that are perfect, we ſpeak the wiſdom of God in a myſtery,</hi> Verſe 7. Thus the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms himſelf to thoſe he ſpeaks to; as he can live with the higheſt in Canaan, ſo he can goe down into Egypt to take his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by the hand, to the end he may bring them from one degree to another, untill they are come to ſit with himſelf in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places: He was not ſo high with thoſe to whom he ſpeaks wiſdom in a myſterie; but he is as low, where he ſaith, <hi>And I bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. could not ſpeak unto you, as unto ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, but as unto carnall, even as unto babes in Chriſt: I have fed you with milk, not with meat, for hitherto you were not able to bear it, neither yet now are ye able,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:169878:56"/>
1 Cor. 2. 1, 2. He became all thing to all men, that he might gain ſome: Alſo, he ſaith, Hebr. 5. 12, 13, 14. <hi>For when for the time ye ought to be Teachers, ye have need that one teach you again which be the firſt principles of the Oracles of God, and are ſuch as have need of milk and not of ſtrong meat for every one that uſeth milke is unskilful in the word of righteonſneſs, for he is a babe; but ſtrong meat belongs to them that are of full age,</hi> or in the Greek word, <hi>perfect;</hi> ſince God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſpoken in ſundry times &amp; divers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſpeakes not in one way or one form, therefore let us not perſecute one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; if God ſpeaks not to others in the way he ſpeaks to us, doe not deſire to lord<note place="margin">Rom. 15. 1.</note> it over Gods heritage; we that are ſtrong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak; for who makes thee to differ from another,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 7.</note> and what haſt thou that thou didſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive? now if thou didſt receive it, why doeſt thou glory as if thou hadſt not received it? before thou receiv'dſt it thou waſt as he, thou thinkeſt meanly of; wouldſt thou have been willing to have been deſpiſed and ſtumbled and ſo deſtroyed when thou wert weak be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou hadſt received this grace? and if not, lay not ſtumbling blocks in thy brothers way; therefore ſince we come up all one way to perfection, let every one of us be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169878:57"/>
reconciled one to another, let every one of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 2.</note> us pleaſe his neighbour for his good to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; let us therfore as many as be perfect be thus minded, and if in any thing you be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveale even this unto you, nevertheleſs whereunto you have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule. Now the God of patience and conſolation grant you to be like minded one towards another according to Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THe Objection which ſaith, <hi>That no man hath the knowledg that Adam bad before his fall, to give the creatures names according to their natures, as he did; they being deprived of that underſtanding by his fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, thus, It remains for you to prove, that there was any creature in paradiſe, which I am ſure you cannot; for we find, firſt, that man was put into paradiſe <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 8. And 2ly. he is drove out of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 23. Here you ſee the mans bringing in, and his driving out, but no creatures are brought in, or driven out with him; therefore leſt you can prove that the creatures were there, I ſhall deny that he named them there.</p>
            <p>2. We are not to underſtand, that the Scriptures are fulfilled in order as they are written; for if ſo, then <hi>Adam</hi> and all the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169878:57"/>
creatures were twice made; for in the fifth days work, the fiſh of the ſea, and the fowl of the air were created, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 18 to 23. and in the beginning of the ſix days, the living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the earth were created, cattel and creeping things after their kind, <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25. &amp; then man was created, <hi>v.</hi> 27. All things are ſaid to be made, and God is ſaid to end his work, and reſt, and yet Chap. 2. <hi>v.</hi> 5. it is ſaid, <hi>There is no man to till the ground;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 7. it is ſaid, <hi>That the Lord God formed man of the duſt of the ground;</hi> although before in Chap. 1. the Creatures are ſaid to be made before man: yet here in this Chapter, man is ſaid to be made again, and the creatures after him; for he is ſaid to be made, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and they, <hi>v.</hi> 19. Again, for all it's ſaid, Male and Female created he them, and alſo that he had ended his works, and did reſt from them, Chap. 2. v. 2. yet you will finde, that the Woman was made afterwards, as it is ver. 22. And therefore I ſay, the Scriptures are not to be underſtood in order as they are written; but many times, when a thing is ſaid to be done, it is done many hundred years after; and ſo alſo is this touching our naming of creatures, and our ruling over them, and our freedome to eat of every hearb or fruit of the earth; if any one of theſe things is attributed to <hi>Adam,</hi> and not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169878:58"/>
to us: then by the ſame grounds, the other, as ruling, tilling, dreſſing and eating of the fruit or hearbs muſt be attributed to him, and not to us; but we are <hi>Adam</hi> as well as he, it is to us God brings the creatures, to ſee what names we will call them.</p>
            <p>3. According to you own underſtanding of Scripture, <hi>Adam</hi> did manifeſt knowledg and wiſdom after his fall, as well as before, as you may ſee after judgment pronounc'd upon him, <hi>Chap. 3. v.</hi> 20. it is ſaid, Adam cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his wife <hi>Eve,</hi> becauſe ſhe was the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all living. So then, if he had wiſdom and knowledg to name the creatures before his fall, it was a greater piece of wiſdom to name one more excellent then the ſenſitive creatures, and alſo to give the reaſon of her name, becauſe ſhe was the mother of all living, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 20.</p>
            <p>4. There is nothing now in the Old-Teſtament named either by good men or bad, but ſignifieth either good or bad: God can ſpeak in <hi>Caiaphas</hi> touching the great ſacrifice, or reprove <hi>Balaam</hi> by his Aſs, yet neither of theſe knew what they ſpake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> Objection <hi>was omitted, and I hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſome moving of it, thought fit to point at this anſwer for the preſent ſatisfaction of the Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
